<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Antichrist's government justly detected of unrighteousness, injustice, unreasonableness, oppression, and cruelty throughout the kingdomes of this world, wherein Antichrist hath had his seat and great authority for many generations ... / by Edward Burroughs.</title>
            <author>Burrough, Edward, 1634-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 176KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B18337</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12047166</idno>
  <idno type="VID">199695</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240961992</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5985</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12047166</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B18337)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 199695)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 861:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Antichrist's government justly detected of unrighteousness, injustice, unreasonableness, oppression, and cruelty throughout the kingdomes of this world, wherein Antichrist hath had his seat and great authority for many generations ... / by Edward Burroughs.</title>
                  <author>Burrough, Edward, 1634-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 49 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 49.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Christianity and politics.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Church and the world.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:199695:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199695:1"/>
            <p>Antichrist's Government Justly Detected Of <hi>Ʋnrighteousness, Injustice, Ʋnreasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleness, Oppression,</hi> and <hi>Cruelty;</hi> Throughout the KINGDOMES OF THIS WORLD; Wherein <hi>Antichrist</hi> hath had his <hi>Seat</hi> and great <hi>Authority</hi> for many Generations, in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stacy from the Spirit and life of true Christianity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shewed and declared,</hi> First, In the Case of <hi>Imposing</hi> upon <hi>Conscience</hi> in matters Religious, by <hi>force</hi> of outward <hi>Violence,</hi> or <hi>Pains</hi> and <hi>Penalties</hi> on the <hi>Persons</hi> and <hi>Estates</hi> of men, which is proved unrighteous and dangerous, and of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In the Case of <hi>Heresie;</hi> shewing what it is in it self, who a <hi>Heretick</hi> is, who are the true <hi>Judges</hi> of it, and what <hi>Punishment</hi> pertains to such as are truly convicted thereof; and, That to <hi>Kill, Burn, Banish,</hi> or to punish <hi>Hereticks</hi> (as such) <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally,</hi> is of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By <hi>EDWARD BURROUGHS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilson,</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:199695:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199695:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE DEDICATED To all the Rulers (of what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree soever) in the (so called) <hi>Christian VVorld.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>O Friends! <hi>In the perfect Love of God Almighty towards your Souls and Bodies, and towards all Mankind; which Love is as a</hi> Fountain <hi>opened in my heart, &amp; kindly issueth forth in</hi> Soul-breathing-desires <hi>of</hi> good, <hi>unto the</hi> whole Creation. <hi>In this</hi> Love (<hi>joined with an</hi> humble, meek <hi>and</hi> lowly <hi>temper of</hi> spirit) <hi>do I present this little quantity of</hi> substance <hi>unto you; not so much for your</hi> approof <hi>of my</hi> Work, <hi>as if I craved your</hi> License <hi>and</hi> Approbation <hi>for this</hi> small Piece <hi>to pass under your</hi> justificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (<hi>as is usually the manner of such</hi> Epistles <hi>thus directed;) but much more, for your</hi> serious <hi>and</hi> weighty <hi>considerations of the</hi> Cases (<hi>though</hi> briefly, <hi>yet</hi> truly) <hi>unfolded, which are things of very great moment to you; and wherein</hi> All <hi>of you, from the</hi> least <hi>to the</hi> greatest, <hi>are</hi> less <hi>or</hi> more <hi>concerned: And I do present this</hi> Work <hi>unto you as</hi> wholesome Advice, <hi>and</hi> good Counsel <hi>for you, (which ye ought ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily to</hi> read <hi>and</hi> receive <hi>as such) rather then to flatter you by begging a</hi> Passe-port <hi>from you, that this may be</hi> read <hi>and</hi> received <hi>where it shall come; for the</hi> truth <hi>and</hi> verity <hi>of it, the</hi> weight <hi>of the matter contained, and the</hi> soundness <hi>of</hi> substance <hi>demonstrated, shall plead its own</hi> worth <hi>for acceptation in the</hi> Hearts <hi>and</hi> Consciences <hi>of all</hi> sincere men. <hi>The</hi> Truth <hi>and</hi> Verity, Weight <hi>and</hi> Substance <hi>of</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:199695:3"/> Matter: <hi>I say, These</hi> Terms <hi>I may justly present this</hi> small Piece <hi>under the denomination of, unto</hi> you, <hi>and all the</hi> world. <hi>True it is, I do not study</hi> pleasing Stile, <hi>nor have I endeavoured to</hi> clothe <hi>and</hi> trim <hi>the</hi> Matter <hi>with</hi> flattery, curious tearms, words of man's wisdom, <hi>or some</hi> rare Method, <hi>that it might appear more in</hi> shew, <hi>than in</hi> real substance, (<hi>as the way of too many</hi> Writers <hi>hath been in such cases;) nor do I promise to please the</hi> Worldly Wisdom <hi>in men, by a</hi> delightful sound, <hi>so much as to answer the</hi> sincere Conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <hi>of men by</hi> sound Truths, <hi>declared more in</hi> homely, broken tearms of speech, <hi>than in the</hi> rarity <hi>of</hi> Phrase, <hi>or</hi> well-compact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Rhetorick; <hi>For I have always desired to be known and approved of</hi> God, <hi>and</hi> those <hi>that fear him, in</hi> sincerity, humility, <hi>and</hi> down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right truth; <hi>and for this I</hi> study <hi>daily, and</hi> labour <hi>always, even to have</hi> praise, peace <hi>and</hi> comfort <hi>of</hi> God, <hi>rather than</hi> men, <hi>in what I</hi> am, <hi>and in what I</hi> do; <hi>and therefore 'tis my desire that ye would look beyond the</hi> Method containing, <hi>to the</hi> Matter contained, <hi>and that your eye may be onely fixed on the</hi> Substance <hi>intended, which is verily, and in truth, That ye may be informed the way of your</hi> peace <hi>and</hi> happiness <hi>in</hi> this <hi>world, and in</hi> that <hi>which is to come; and may never hereafter</hi> impose <hi>by</hi> force <hi>and</hi> violence <hi>in the matters of</hi> Faith, <hi>and the</hi> Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of God, <hi>upon the</hi> Consciences <hi>of any, through</hi> penalties <hi>and</hi> punishments <hi>upon mens</hi> Persons <hi>and</hi> Estates, <hi>but that ye may</hi> allow <hi>and</hi> tollerate <hi>freely,</hi> Liberty of Conscience <hi>in all</hi> Religious Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>and may not by</hi> cruelty <hi>destroy men in their</hi> Persons <hi>or</hi> Estates, <hi>upon the account of their being supposed to be, or if really</hi> Hereticks, <hi>and because of difference in</hi> Judgement <hi>and</hi> Practice, <hi>in</hi> Spiritual Matters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>These are the</hi> particulars (<hi>for</hi> substance) <hi>held forth unto you, and all the world; and I have judged it most proper to direct these</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses <hi>to your</hi> view <hi>and</hi> consideration, <hi>as being the persons</hi> most chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (<hi>though</hi> not wholly) <hi>concerned: therefore</hi> blame me not, <hi>but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> receive <hi>my</hi> Love, <hi>though but</hi> little <hi>in</hi> quantity, <hi>yet</hi> real <hi>in</hi> quality, <hi>and that ye will find one day, when ye have</hi> truly tried <hi>the</hi> effects <hi>of the</hi> two Cases <hi>plainly laid before you, which are,</hi> Impositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon Conscience, <hi>and,</hi> Free Liberty of Conscience; <hi>These are the</hi> two Causes <hi>which will have their</hi> contrary <hi>and</hi> different effects <hi>upon all the</hi> Rulers <hi>in the world;</hi> Peace, Blessings, Prosperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>and</hi> Happiness, <hi>are the</hi> effects <hi>of the</hi> one Cause; <hi>and</hi> Wars, Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,
<pb facs="tcp:199695:3"/> Contentions, Misery, Sorrow <hi>and the</hi> Curse, <hi>are the</hi> ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects <hi>which have, and will unavoidably follow the</hi> other Cause; <hi>and this ye will all find in the</hi> experience <hi>of</hi> Time <hi>and</hi> Transactions, <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to pass in the world: And therefore I cannot but (in</hi> homely, plain words, <hi>as my manner is) assert the</hi> Causes, <hi>and the</hi> effects <hi>of the</hi> Causes, <hi>unto you, again and again, for the very</hi> end, <hi>to</hi> inform <hi>you,</hi> advise <hi>you, and</hi> warn <hi>you to follow the</hi> Good, <hi>and to forsake the</hi> Evil, <hi>to do the</hi> right, <hi>and hate the</hi> wrong, <hi>that the</hi> effects <hi>of</hi> Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness, <hi>and</hi> Liberty of Conscience, <hi>even</hi> Peace, Love, Mercy <hi>and</hi> Prosperity, <hi>may ever be with you; and the</hi> effects <hi>of</hi> Cruelty <hi>and</hi> Oppression, <hi>and</hi> Imposition upon Conscience, <hi>which will be your</hi> misery, downfall <hi>and</hi> destruction (<hi>if ye continue in the</hi> Cause <hi>which works this</hi> Effect) <hi>may be turned away, and ye delivered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherefore O ye men, be</hi> advised, <hi>be</hi> warned; <hi>this is the</hi> day <hi>of the</hi> Lords dawnings; <hi>We have seen his</hi> Power <hi>and</hi> Glory; <hi>he hath</hi> wounded <hi>Us, and</hi> healed <hi>Us, he hath</hi> killed <hi>and made</hi> alive; <hi>he hath proclaimed</hi> Liberty <hi>in Our</hi> Souls <hi>and</hi> Consciences, <hi>from</hi> Death <hi>and Darkness, from the</hi> Grave <hi>and</hi> Hell; <hi>and he hath set his People</hi> free <hi>from</hi> bondage, <hi>to serve him with a</hi> pure <hi>and</hi> perfect heart; <hi>and if ye</hi> (mortal men, <hi>made of the dust of the ground, whose little measure of breath is in your Nostrils) will not</hi> approve of, <hi>and</hi> join with <hi>this</hi> blessed Work <hi>of the</hi> Lord, <hi>but shall gain-say his</hi> doings, <hi>and set</hi> your Power <hi>against</hi> his Power, <hi>and will not let the People go</hi> free <hi>in the exercise of their</hi> Consciences <hi>on</hi> holy performances, <hi>whose</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences <hi>God hath made</hi> free; <hi>then shall the</hi> Most High <hi>reward your</hi> op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position <hi>with his Cup of</hi> Vengeance, <hi>and he will make you know he is the</hi> Lord <hi>against whom ye thus raise</hi> contention; <hi>and he will dissolve</hi> your substance, <hi>and bring down</hi> your glory, <hi>and subdue</hi> your pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>if that (I say) ye</hi> oppose his Work, <hi>and will seek to</hi> bind <hi>and</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit his Spirit <hi>in</hi> his people, <hi>and wil yet</hi> force <hi>and</hi> impose <hi>upon</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science <hi>by</hi> outward violence, <hi>and</hi> kill, <hi>and</hi> persecute <hi>unto</hi> death, <hi>and</hi> banishment <hi>for matter of</hi> Conscience, <hi>and because of difference in</hi> Judgement <hi>in</hi> spiritual things; <hi>then thus it shall be done unto you, Ye shall</hi> fall, <hi>and</hi> perish, <hi>and be</hi> troubled, <hi>and</hi> blessings <hi>and</hi> prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity <hi>shall not be unto you. If it be not thus, the</hi> Lord <hi>hath not spoken by me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Well</hi> Friends, <hi>even all ye that have</hi> Authority <hi>and</hi> Power <hi>in the</hi> Government <hi>of this</hi> World, <hi>are nearly concern'd to take</hi> special no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice <hi>of</hi> these things <hi>presented unto you, seeing the</hi> Effects <hi>of these</hi> two Causes <hi>are both very</hi> weighty, <hi>and</hi> infallibly certain, <hi>even to</hi> you-
<pb facs="tcp:199695:4"/> wards <hi>particularly:</hi> Very weighty, <hi>because</hi> Peace, Prosperity <hi>and</hi> Happiness, <hi>or</hi> Misery, Distractions <hi>and</hi> Downfall <hi>to you is depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the</hi> Effects <hi>of the</hi> Causes; Infallibly certain, <hi>because the</hi> Justice <hi>of</hi> God Almighty <hi>is such, that he must bring</hi> reward <hi>upon all according to</hi> their deeds, <hi>and his</hi> Justice <hi>cannot be diverted: But if ye permit</hi> free Liberty of Conscience <hi>in the</hi> exercise <hi>of</hi> godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse <hi>in</hi> Faith <hi>and</hi> Worship, <hi>unto</hi> all people <hi>under your</hi> Power, <hi>then shall</hi> Peace <hi>and</hi> Prosperity <hi>be unto you, according to the</hi> purpose <hi>of</hi> God: <hi>But if ye</hi> impose upon Conscience <hi>in any wise, by</hi> force <hi>in</hi> Religious matters, <hi>&amp; will not be</hi> instructed <hi>and</hi> advised <hi>to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, then shall</hi> misery <hi>and</hi> destruction <hi>certainly be unto you, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the</hi> Justice <hi>of God's</hi> Vengeance. <hi>These things are</hi> so, <hi>as a</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant <hi>of</hi> God <hi>I present them to you, and not upon</hi> fiction <hi>or</hi> fancy, <hi>but as I have received them from the</hi> Lord God, <hi>by his</hi> Spirit, <hi>which sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies the</hi> verity <hi>and</hi> certainty <hi>of these things in my soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Friends, <hi>Doubt not of these things; for verily the time is at hand, and it must</hi> surely <hi>come to pass, my</hi> Spirit <hi>shall see it, and rejoice therein, if in</hi> this body <hi>I may not behold it, That</hi> imposing <hi>and</hi> forcing <hi>of</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science <hi>by</hi> Laws <hi>and</hi> Ordinances <hi>of Men, upon</hi> penalties <hi>on mens</hi> Persons <hi>and</hi> Estates, <hi>in</hi> Religious matters, <hi>shall be</hi> expunged, sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued <hi>and</hi> abandoned <hi>in</hi> these Nations <hi>&amp;</hi> Kingdoms <hi>of the world, and it shall be no more: But</hi> Liberty, Liberty <hi>shall be</hi> re-planted, embraced <hi>and</hi> renowned <hi>amongst men, and</hi> Truth <hi>and</hi> Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, Mercy <hi>and</hi> Peace, True Liberty <hi>and</hi> Freedom, Justice <hi>and</hi> true Judgement, <hi>with all the</hi> Causes <hi>and</hi> Effects <hi>thereof shall</hi> flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish, <hi>and</hi> grow, <hi>and</hi> prosper <hi>on the Earth, and the</hi> contrary <hi>shall fall, and</hi> rise no more. <hi>This</hi> Day <hi>is drawing nigh, it's at the door, blessed are they that are prepared for it: Wherefore let all flesh</hi> hear <hi>and</hi> fear, bow <hi>and</hi> tremble; <hi>and let the</hi> hearts <hi>of the Righteous</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice <hi>and be</hi> exceeding glad; <hi>let all the</hi> upright in heart <hi>put on the</hi> garment of Praises <hi>and</hi> Deliverance; <hi>for the</hi> Day <hi>is at hand, that</hi> Antichrist (<hi>with all his</hi> Strength <hi>and</hi> Power, Force <hi>and</hi> Policy) <hi>shall be a</hi> hissing, <hi>and</hi> reproach, <hi>and</hi> shame, <hi>and</hi> contempt <hi>unto the</hi> Saints <hi>of the</hi> Most High, <hi>and amongst whom the</hi> Lord God Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent <hi>doth, and must</hi> Reign <hi>and</hi> Rule <hi>in</hi> Dominion, <hi>and</hi> Glory, <hi>and</hi> Power, <hi>over All, for</hi> ever, <hi>and</hi> evermore.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>London <date>
                     <hi>this</hi> 12th. <hi>Month,</hi> 1661.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>E. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:199695:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Concerning <hi>imposing Religion;</hi> the Case stated, and the unrighteousness thereof shewed, with the danger thereof also made appear by manifest proofs. <hi>Presented to the RULERS and PEOPLE of our present Age, throughout the World.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>TO <hi>impose</hi> any <hi>kind</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> any <hi>way</hi> of <hi>Worship,</hi> or <hi>form</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>outward conformity,</hi> in any <hi>practices</hi> of <hi>duty</hi> to <hi>God-wards,</hi> by an <hi>External Authority</hi> of <hi>men,</hi> through <hi>force</hi> of <hi>Laws</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding and requiring <hi>such conformity</hi> in <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Worship,</hi> upon <hi>pains, penalties</hi> and <hi>forfeitures</hi> on mens <hi>Persons</hi> and <hi>Estates,</hi> as hath been practised in the <hi>world</hi> since the <hi>days</hi> of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> among the <hi>Nations</hi> professing <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity; This thing</hi> is not of the <hi>Lord,</hi> nor according to <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and <hi>Examples</hi> of the <hi>Apostles</hi> and <hi>Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,</hi> declared of in the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> but is of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous, unequal</hi> and <hi>dangerous,</hi> to the destruction of the <hi>Souls</hi> and <hi>Bodies</hi> of both the <hi>Imposers,</hi> and the <hi>Imposed.</hi> For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Such</hi> kind of <hi>forcing,</hi> &amp; <hi>compelling</hi> by <hi>force</hi> of <hi>outward Laws,</hi> into <hi>such outward conformity</hi> of <hi>Religion, Faith</hi> and <hi>Worship, Church-Government</hi> and <hi>Ministry,</hi> was <hi>never</hi> in <hi>being</hi> nor <hi>ever practised</hi> in the <hi>true Christian Churches,</hi> amongst the <hi>Apostles</hi> in their <hi>days;</hi> nor ever was such a thing known among the <hi>Primitive Christians;</hi> There was no such kind of <hi>Laws made</hi> nor <hi>executed</hi> amongst
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:199695:5"/> them, nor such <hi>force exercised</hi> on men's <hi>persons</hi> and <hi>estates</hi> in <hi>such cases;</hi> there was no <hi>outward violence</hi> used in the <hi>primitive times,</hi> to <hi>compell</hi> any to <hi>conformity</hi> to <hi>Christian Faith, Worship,</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> of <hi>Christian Religion;</hi> none of the <hi>first Christians</hi> were made <hi>truly Religious,</hi> and <hi>converted</hi> from the <hi>way of Error,</hi> to the <hi>way of true Christianity</hi> by such means of <hi>outward force</hi> and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments</hi> of men put upon them; They were not (I say) <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted</hi> themselves to the <hi>Christian Faith</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> nor made <hi>conformable worshippers</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in his <hi>Spirit</hi> by <hi>that way</hi> and <hi>means,</hi> nor did they seek to convert others into <hi>conformity</hi> to <hi>Church-Government</hi> and <hi>Christian Worship</hi> by <hi>force</hi> of <hi>outward Laws,</hi> upon <hi>pains</hi> and <hi>forfeitures; These things</hi> were not in the <hi>true Church</hi> of <hi>Christ in</hi> the <hi>Apostles</hi> days amongst the <hi>Primitive Christians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. But the <hi>true way of Conversion</hi> among them, to the <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Faith,</hi> and <hi>Worship,</hi> and <hi>true Church-Government,</hi> whereby peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were made rightly <hi>conformable</hi> to the <hi>true Christian Religion,</hi> as it was amongst the <hi>Apostles;</hi> was by and through the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Gospel</hi> of <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> preached amongst them in the <hi>power</hi> and <hi>demonstration</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> of such as were <hi>truly called</hi> and <hi>sent</hi> of him, which did turn people to the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and that <hi>Ministery</hi> wrought in them to receive it, by which their <hi>consciences</hi> were <hi>convinced,</hi> and their <hi>hearts perswaded</hi> in the <hi>love</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> to <hi>believe</hi> in him, and <hi>receive</hi> him, and <hi>follow</hi> him; and thus were they <hi>drawn,</hi> and <hi>begotten,</hi> and <hi>converted</hi> into the <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Worship,</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> of the <hi>true Christian Religion,</hi> and made <hi>conformable</hi> to the <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> of the <hi>true Church</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> in all things, by this <hi>means;</hi> and <hi>were</hi> only, and not at all by any <hi>outward force</hi> and <hi>compulsion</hi> exercised upon them, <hi>converted</hi> to the <hi>true Christian Religion,</hi> and to the <hi>true Worship</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> and by the same way did they <hi>convert</hi> and <hi>turn</hi> others to the <hi>same;</hi> and this onely is the perfect way of <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Conformity</hi> to the <hi>true Christian-Worship</hi> and <hi>Church-Government;</hi> it ever was since the beginning of <hi>Christianity</hi> in the world, and is unto this day, even to <hi>perswade</hi> the <hi>heart,</hi> and to <hi>convince</hi> the <hi>Conscience</hi> inwardly by the <hi>sound Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Gospel,</hi> through the operation of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and by <hi>love,</hi> and <hi>meekness,</hi> and <hi>patience,</hi> and all the <hi>fruits</hi> of <hi>righteousness,</hi> held forth in <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> and <hi>Conversation,</hi> which may answer the <hi>Testimony</hi> of <hi>God</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:199695:5"/> in all mens <hi>Consciences:</hi> Hereby, and in this way is <hi>true Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion</hi> wrought in the <hi>heart,</hi> to the turning men from all <hi>Error</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Truth,</hi> and from all <hi>false Worships,</hi> and <hi>Heresies,</hi> and <hi>evil wayes,</hi> unto the <hi>true Christian Worship,</hi> and <hi>conformity</hi> to <hi>holy Church</hi> and <hi>Religion:</hi> This (I say) was the way among the <hi>primitive Christians</hi> and <hi>Apostles</hi> of <hi>old,</hi> and is the same among the <hi>true Christians</hi> in <hi>this age;</hi> and they that would <hi>conform</hi> others, and are <hi>conformed</hi> themselves otherwise in this <hi>Case</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Worship</hi> to <hi>God-wards,</hi> are not in the <hi>Example</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Saints,</hi> but out of the <hi>Life,</hi> and contrary to the <hi>first Christians,</hi> and <hi>president</hi> of the <hi>holy Scriptures,</hi> as hereafter is manifested.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>way</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> of <hi>imposing Religion,</hi> and <hi>Conformity</hi> in <hi>Worship</hi> and <hi>Church-Government,</hi> by <hi>Force,</hi> (as aforesaid) is so far from being <hi>according</hi> to the <hi>Practice</hi> and <hi>Example</hi> of the <hi>Apostles</hi> and the <hi>primitive Churches</hi> of <hi>Christians,</hi> that they are even <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary</hi> to the <hi>Commands</hi> and <hi>Exhortations</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles,</hi> and <hi>Example</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures:</hi> 1. As in the <hi>Parable</hi> of the <hi>Wheat</hi> and the <hi>Tares, Matt.</hi> 13. when it was desired of the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, that they might go and gather out the <hi>Tares</hi> that the <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> had sown, from among the <hi>Wheat;</hi> it was commanded to the contrary by the <hi>Husbandman,</hi> even that they should suffer the <hi>Tares</hi> to grow among the <hi>Wheat</hi> till the <hi>Harvest,</hi> and not pluck them up, lest they should hurt the <hi>Wheat</hi> thereby. Now though there be an <hi>invisible Mysterie</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> secret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly signified in this <hi>Parable,</hi> more then may here be said; yet 'tis also clearly signified, that <hi>Christ</hi> would have no <hi>imposition</hi> nor <hi>violence</hi> used upon the <hi>Tares,</hi> nor that they should pluck them up by force, but that the <hi>good Corn</hi> and the <hi>bad</hi> should grow to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in one <hi>Field</hi> till the <hi>Harvest.</hi> And thus much this <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> bears the proof of: Suppose there be <hi>Heresies</hi> and <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and <hi>prophane persons</hi> that are not in the <hi>truth,</hi> but in <hi>errors,</hi> who are <hi>bad Corn,</hi> even as the <hi>Tares</hi> to the <hi>Wheat;</hi> in that <hi>Kingdom, City</hi> or <hi>Family</hi> where there is also <hi>converted Saints,</hi> and <hi>holy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,</hi> and <hi>true Members</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> who are as the <hi>Wheat</hi> to the <hi>Tares;</hi> yet such <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>prophane persons</hi> that are in <hi>Error,</hi> ought not to be plucked up violently, to wit, <hi>Imprisoned, banish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> and put to <hi>death, burned</hi> and <hi>destroyed</hi> from amongst the <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous,</hi> though they grow amongst them, even in the same <hi>Field;</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:199695:6"/> the <hi>converted Saints</hi> ought not (I say) to destroy by <hi>banishment</hi> or <hi>death,</hi> the <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and <hi>unconverted,</hi> and <hi>unconformable</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons from amongst them, but they are to let them <hi>live,</hi> even <hi>grow</hi> amongst them in the <hi>same Field,</hi> in the <hi>same Kingdom, City</hi> or <hi>Family,</hi> till <hi>Harvest.</hi> And thus much the <hi>Parable</hi> may truly signifie, even a <hi>liberty</hi> to live for the <hi>Tares,</hi> the <hi>bad Corn,</hi> the <hi>evil persons,</hi> among the <hi>Wheat,</hi> the <hi>righteous persons,</hi> without being <hi>imposed</hi> upon by cruel <hi>force</hi> and outward <hi>violence,</hi> to <hi>compel</hi> into <hi>conformity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As in the case among the <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>true believers,</hi> where some believed they might eat <hi>all things,</hi> others did eat <hi>Herbs;</hi> and some <hi>esteemed one day above another,</hi> and others <hi>esteemed every day alike,</hi> Rom. 14. Here was some <hi>difference</hi> in <hi>Judgement</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> among the <hi>Believers,</hi> about <hi>Meats</hi> and <hi>Dayes</hi> (about which things there hath been much <hi>Imposition</hi> and <hi>Force</hi> used in the World since the <hi>Apostles</hi> dayes:) Well, but what doth the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> do, and advise in this case? Doth he threaten <hi>violence</hi> towards any of them, or signifie any forcible <hi>commands</hi> or <hi>impositions</hi> to be used to bring them into <hi>conformity</hi> and <hi>unity</hi> in the things and matters about which they were divided? No, no; but this is his <hi>advice</hi> to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> (of which he was a <hi>true</hi> and <hi>able Minister</hi>) Judge not one another about <hi>such things,</hi> nor do not <hi>impose</hi> any <hi>practice</hi> upon thy <hi>Brother;</hi> for to <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> his <hi>Master,</hi> every <hi>Believer stands</hi> or <hi>falls.</hi> And saith the Apostle, <hi>Let every man be fully perswaded in his own mind,</hi> ver. 5 And hereby 'tis manifestly proved, that in the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Christians,</hi> the <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>true Christians</hi> were not <hi>imposed</hi> upon by <hi>commandments</hi> of men, or outward Laws, in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of their <hi>Religion,</hi> and practice of <hi>Conscience;</hi> there was no signification of <hi>Force</hi> to be used for <hi>Conformity;</hi> but wholly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, even every <hi>believer</hi> had the liberty of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and as he was by that perswaded in his own mind, to <hi>do,</hi> or leave <hi>undone</hi> in such cases, and every one was to mind the <hi>teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> in himself, for to <hi>that</hi> he was to <hi>stand</hi> or <hi>fall,</hi> and not to <hi>impose</hi> upon another, no not so much as to <hi>judge</hi> his <hi>Brother</hi> in any case of difference in <hi>judgement</hi> or <hi>practise,</hi> but they were to leave one another to the perswasions of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> in their own minds.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:199695:6"/>3. As in the <hi>Case</hi> where the <hi>Apostle</hi> exhorted the Saints to be <hi>like-minded,</hi> Phil. 3. But saith he, <hi>If any be otherwise minded, God shall reveal even this unto you;</hi> by which saying it is manifest, that the <hi>Unity</hi> and <hi>Conformity</hi> of <hi>Saints</hi> in <hi>mind</hi> and <hi>practice,</hi> was not by <hi>Imposition,</hi> or any <hi>outward force threatned</hi> or exercised upon their <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</hi> or <hi>Estates;</hi> but contrariwise, if there was any <hi>difference</hi> in <hi>mind</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> amongst them, <hi>that</hi> was to be <hi>amended,</hi> and <hi>Unity</hi> made up, when <hi>God</hi> revealed the <hi>same truth</hi> in <hi>all,</hi> as he had done in <hi>some;</hi> if <hi>any</hi> were not <hi>so minded</hi> in any thing as <hi>others</hi> were; they were not to be <hi>imposed</hi> upon, but let <hi>God</hi> reveal the <hi>same,</hi> and bring into <hi>conformity;</hi> this was the <hi>Apostle's Counsel:</hi> And ver. 16 <hi>Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less, whereto we have already attained, let us walk by the same Rule;</hi> that is to say, so far as the <hi>Rule</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> is <hi>made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest,</hi> or in what <hi>measure</hi> the <hi>perfection</hi> thereof is <hi>attained unto,</hi> let <hi>every one walk</hi> in the <hi>same measure,</hi> and by the <hi>same Rule;</hi> and if any have not the <hi>self-same measure</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and knows the <hi>self same things,</hi> let such alone, without <hi>imposing</hi> upon them, leave them to walk in the <hi>measure</hi> of <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Knowledge</hi> that they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, though it be not the <hi>self-same measure</hi> that <hi>others</hi> have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; and if they want any <hi>knowledge,</hi> or be in any thing <hi>other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise minded, God</hi> shall <hi>reveal</hi> the <hi>same</hi> unto them, even the <hi>same thing,</hi> as they grow in the <hi>same measure</hi> of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge:</hi> And here is the <hi>perfect way</hi> of <hi>Unity</hi> and <hi>Conformity,</hi> as the <hi>Primitive Christians</hi> were exercised in the <hi>true Faith</hi> and <hi>Worship,</hi> and <hi>true Christian Religion</hi> in <hi>their days:</hi> And so to <hi>impose</hi> by <hi>Force</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>pains</hi> and <hi>forfeitures</hi> in <hi>Religious matters,</hi> is <hi>clearly contrary</hi> to <hi>all</hi> these <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and to many more in the <hi>New-Testament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. In that case 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.2, 3. where the <hi>Apostle</hi> exhorts the <hi>Elders</hi> to take the <hi>oversight</hi> of <hi>Gods Flock, not by constraint or force, but willingly; not for filthy lucre, but of a ready mind; neither as being Lords over Gods Heritage:</hi> Which clearly signifies against <hi>imposing</hi> upon the <hi>Flock</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>forcing</hi> in <hi>Religious Matters;</hi> for ye see the <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> might not be <hi>constrained</hi> or <hi>forced</hi> to take the <hi>oversight</hi> of the <hi>Flock;</hi> neither (having the <hi>oversight</hi> of <hi>it</hi>) might they be as <hi>Lords</hi> over <hi>it,</hi> nor <hi>exercise Lordship</hi> over the <hi>Heritage</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> to wit, not <hi>command</hi> the <hi>Faith</hi> of <hi>any,</hi> nor <hi>impose</hi> by any <hi>force,</hi> in <hi>matters</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> or <hi>Duty,</hi> nor <hi>oppress</hi> the <hi>pure Conscience</hi> of <hi>any,</hi> nor be as <hi>Lords</hi> (in <hi>any case</hi>) over the <hi>Heritage,</hi> nor use any <hi>Lordliness,</hi> or <hi>Master<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:199695:7"/> or <hi>Dominion,</hi> or <hi>Commandment</hi> by <hi>force,</hi> or <hi>imposing</hi> upon the <hi>Flock;</hi> this is <hi>clearly forbidden</hi> by the <hi>Apostle,</hi> and the <hi>contrary</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended; <hi>But be ensamples to the Flock,</hi> (saith he) <hi>feed them, win them, teach them,</hi> or <hi>oversee them,</hi> by <hi>good example,</hi> by <hi>love,</hi> as <hi>good Elders</hi> or <hi>Stewards</hi> over them, not as <hi>Lords,</hi> exercising any <hi>force</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them in <hi>rigor</hi> or <hi>bitterness;</hi> and this is the <hi>perfect way</hi> of <hi>Bishops, Elders</hi> and <hi>Ministers, overseeing</hi> the <hi>Flock</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> even to <hi>rule over,</hi> and <hi>oversee God's Heritage,</hi> walking before them as <hi>good Examples</hi> of <hi>humility, self-denial,</hi> and in <hi>all</hi> the <hi>vertues</hi> and <hi>fruits</hi> of the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and <hi>feeding</hi> them hereby with the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi> and that <hi>freely,</hi> not for <hi>filthy lucre, hire</hi> or <hi>rewards;</hi> and not <hi>ruling over them</hi> as <hi>Lords, imposing</hi> upon them, or <hi>exercising Lordship,</hi> by <hi>forcing</hi> and <hi>commanding</hi> such <hi>Faith, Worship</hi> and <hi>Duty,</hi> and <hi>imprisoning</hi> and <hi>persecuting</hi> for <hi>disobedience</hi> of such <hi>forcing, violent commands,</hi> as hath been <hi>practised</hi> in the <hi>World</hi> for <hi>many Ages,</hi> even <hi>Lordliness</hi> exercised over the <hi>Heritage</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Ministers, Pastors</hi> and <hi>Elders</hi> have been as <hi>Lords</hi> over the <hi>Flock,</hi> and ruled by <hi>force</hi> and <hi>imposition,</hi> contrary to the <hi>example</hi> of <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and the <hi>Commands</hi> of the <hi>Apostles;</hi> and <hi>Love, Meekness, Gentleness,</hi> and <hi>good Example,</hi> have been neglected, contrary to the <hi>Apostle Peter</hi>'s Instructions.</p>
            <p>Thus it is clearly manifest throughout the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> by many <hi>proofs,</hi> that the way of <hi>imposing Religion,</hi> and <hi>forcing</hi> into the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity</hi> of <hi>Worship</hi> and <hi>Church-Government,</hi> in the <hi>dispensation</hi> of the <hi>Gospel,</hi> as aforesaid, is contrary to the <hi>commands</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Apostles,</hi> and the <hi>example</hi> of <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and is not of <hi>God,</hi> nor according unto him. And now I shall shew in the <hi>fourth place,</hi> of <hi>whom</hi> it is, and by <hi>whose Example</hi> this <hi>violence</hi> used, and <hi>persecution,</hi> unto <hi>Imprisonment</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> for, and because of <hi>Religion,</hi> and also the <hi>beginning</hi> of <hi>imposition</hi> by force amongst <hi>Christians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>All</hi> this <hi>Persecution</hi> practised about <hi>Religion,</hi> that hath been in the <hi>world,</hi> as <hi>Imprisonments, Banishments, VVhippings, cruel Tortures</hi> unto <hi>death,</hi> and <hi>grievous Affliction,</hi> hath been of the <hi>wicked one,</hi> through the <hi>Malice</hi> and <hi>Envy</hi> of the <hi>Devil,</hi> against <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>People</hi> in all <hi>Generations,</hi> even all that <hi>Persecution</hi> exercised towards the <hi>Prophets</hi> of old, before the <hi>coming</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> in the <hi>Flesh,</hi> it would be too large to relate the <hi>particulars</hi> of it, as it is signified partly in the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and chiefly in the <hi>Records</hi> of <hi>Transactions</hi> in <hi>their dayes;</hi> and I perceive it will easily be acknowledged by <hi>all,</hi> that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:199695:7"/> such <hi>cruel Persecutions</hi> were of the <hi>Devil.</hi> And again, in the days of <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Apostles,</hi> how <hi>great</hi> was that <hi>force</hi> and <hi>impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition</hi> by <hi>Persecution,</hi> practised upon the <hi>true primitive Christians,</hi> by the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Heathens,</hi> even that <hi>Persecution</hi> which was <hi>inflicted</hi> upon <hi>Christ,</hi> his <hi>Apostles,</hi> and the <hi>Christians,</hi> was <hi>imposition</hi> and <hi>force</hi> exercised about <hi>Religion,</hi> though not so much for <hi>compelling</hi> them to any thing, as from that way of <hi>Righteousness</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> in which they <hi>walked;</hi> they were <hi>commanded to preach no more in the Name of Jesus,</hi> and were <hi>imprisoned, banished,</hi> and <hi>greatly afflicted</hi> by the <hi>Jews</hi> (that <hi>great professing people</hi>) for, and because of their <hi>Religion;</hi> and this for the <hi>first</hi> and <hi>second Ages:</hi> I need not mention the <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar proofs</hi> for <hi>this thing,</hi> 'tis so clear throughout the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles,</hi> and <hi>else-where,</hi> how the <hi>Primitive Christians</hi> were <hi>forced</hi> and <hi>imposed</hi> upon by <hi>cruel Laws,</hi> and <hi>violent persecutions</hi> for their <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Religion</hi> sake; all which <hi>force</hi> and <hi>imposed persecutions,</hi> were of the <hi>Devil,</hi> out of his <hi>envy</hi> and <hi>malice raised</hi> up, and <hi>begotten</hi> in the <hi>hearts</hi> of <hi>wicked men,</hi> against <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>elected People;</hi> and this will be acknowledged by <hi>all.</hi> But</p>
            <p n="5">5. This <hi>way</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> of <hi>imposing</hi> upon <hi>people</hi> by <hi>force,</hi> and <hi>compelling</hi> them to <hi>conformity</hi> in <hi>matters</hi> of <hi>Worship</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> this <hi>persecution</hi> about the <hi>same,</hi> was never known in the <hi>world</hi> amongst <hi>Christians,</hi> nor <hi>practised</hi> by any called <hi>Christians,</hi> till the <hi>Apostasie,</hi> and <hi>falling away</hi> from the <hi>true Faith,</hi> which some did in the <hi>dayes</hi> of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> and many more <hi>afterwards;</hi> for even in the <hi>Apostles dayes</hi> some were <hi>gone out from them</hi> into the way of <hi>Cain</hi> that <hi>killed</hi> his <hi>Brother,</hi> and into the way of <hi>Balaam,</hi> that went for <hi>gifts</hi> and <hi>rewards;</hi> and these were <hi>Apostates</hi> from the <hi>true Church,</hi> and they were <hi>heady, high-minded men, proud, covetous, false accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sers,</hi> and such like, as <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy</hi> expresseth; such as these were already sprung up in the <hi>first Age,</hi> and they <hi>grew</hi> more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly in the <hi>second Age;</hi> and these were the <hi>Antichrists</hi> and <hi>false Prophets</hi> which <hi>John</hi> saw were <hi>gone out from the true Church,</hi> into the <hi>world,</hi> in <hi>his time;</hi> and these <hi>deceived</hi> the <hi>world</hi> by the <hi>form</hi> of <hi>godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,</hi> and the <hi>likeness</hi> of <hi>Christianity,</hi> without the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ;</hi> and the <hi>Apostates</hi> from the <hi>true Faith</hi> which were <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spread</hi> in <hi>many Nations,</hi> and <hi>grown numerous,</hi> were the <hi>Sea</hi> and the <hi>Earth,</hi> out of which the <hi>Beasts</hi> arose, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. <hi>And it was given to the Beast to make war with the Saints, and to overcome them, and they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:199695:8"/> that dwell upon the Earth should worship him; and he should</hi> CAUSE <hi>the Earth, and them that dwell therein, to worship; and he should</hi> CAUSE <hi>as many as would not worship the Beast and his Image, should be killed; and he should</hi> CAUSE <hi>all, both small and great, rich and poor, bond and free, to receive his Mark, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>this Beast</hi> was the <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> of <hi>Antichrist</hi> that arose among the <hi>Apostates</hi> and the <hi>false Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> that thus <hi>CAUSED</hi> and <hi>compelled</hi> all to <hi>worship</hi> the <hi>Beast</hi> and his <hi>Image;</hi> Mark how often the word <hi>CAUSED</hi> is used in that <hi>Chapter,</hi> which is <hi>compelled</hi> or <hi>forced,</hi> and it was the <hi>Antichrist,</hi> the <hi>Beast</hi> that did <hi>it,</hi> the <hi>Authority</hi> that arose among the <hi>Apostate Christians</hi> that were gone from the <hi>true Church;</hi> and this was the <hi>first</hi> that we read of any <hi>forcing</hi> or <hi>compelling</hi> to <hi>worship,</hi> or <hi>persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> about <hi>Worship,</hi> and <hi>imposing</hi> about the same, since the <hi>dayes</hi> of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> through <hi>Ages,</hi> amongst them called <hi>Christians;</hi> and here was the <hi>beginning</hi> of <hi>imposing</hi> by <hi>force,</hi> and <hi>violent Laws,</hi> in the <hi>matters</hi> of <hi>Worship</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> amongst the <hi>People</hi> called <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and one <hi>Sect</hi> and <hi>sort</hi> according to its <hi>Authority, imposed</hi> by <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>force</hi> upon another, <hi>causing,</hi> and <hi>compelling</hi> one another to <hi>worship</hi> and <hi>believe</hi> according to <hi>his Form</hi> and <hi>Image;</hi> and as any <hi>Sect</hi> of <hi>Christians</hi> hath gained <hi>outward Authority</hi> over others, <hi>that same</hi> hath <hi>caused</hi> and <hi>forced</hi> all others by <hi>outward violence</hi> into <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity</hi> to <hi>its</hi> own <hi>way</hi> and <hi>worship;</hi> and this hath been amongst the <hi>People</hi> called <hi>Christians,</hi> in the <hi>Apostasie,</hi> ever since <hi>Antichrist</hi> and <hi>his Power</hi> rose up amongst them; and <hi>thus,</hi> and at <hi>this time</hi> began <hi>first</hi> the <hi>imposing</hi> of <hi>Worship,</hi> and <hi>persecuting</hi> about the <hi>same</hi> amongst <hi>Christians:</hi> And thus 'tis manifest to be of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and of the <hi>wicked one,</hi> and not of the <hi>Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. By what is said, it is plain, That all in this <hi>present Age</hi> who <hi>impose</hi> by <hi>force</hi> of <hi>Laws,</hi> and <hi>compell</hi> to <hi>worship</hi> and <hi>persecute</hi> about the <hi>same,</hi> are not in the <hi>example</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> or his <hi>Apostles,</hi> or any the <hi>good Primitive Christians,</hi> but in so doing are in the <hi>example</hi> of the <hi>Persecutors</hi> of the <hi>Holy Prophets,</hi> and in the <hi>example</hi> of the <hi>cruel Jews</hi> that <hi>killed Christ,</hi> and <hi>persecuted</hi> the <hi>Saints;</hi> and in the <hi>example</hi> of the <hi>cruel Heathens,</hi> that <hi>violently persecuted</hi> the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians</hi> in <hi>divers Ages</hi> and <hi>Countreys,</hi> and are indeed of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and of the <hi>Beast,</hi> that arose up against the <hi>Saints,</hi> and made <hi>war</hi> against <hi>them;</hi> and <hi>such</hi> are <hi>all</hi> they that do <hi>impose</hi> upon the <hi>Persons, Estates</hi> and <hi>Consciences</hi> of <hi>men</hi> at <hi>this day,</hi> upon the account afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said; and this is <hi>worthy</hi> of <hi>all</hi> mens <hi>serious consideration.</hi> And now
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:199695:8"/> in the <hi>next place</hi> I shall proceed to shew how <hi>unrighteous</hi> and <hi>unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable</hi> it is for any called <hi>Christians</hi> to <hi>impose</hi> upon the <hi>Conscience</hi> of <hi>others,</hi> and to <hi>force</hi> them by <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Commandments</hi> in the <hi>matters of Worship,</hi> and to <hi>persecute</hi> about the <hi>same.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. It is <hi>unrighteous,</hi> because it is an <hi>intruding</hi> upon the <hi>Prerogative</hi> and <hi>Priviledge</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and seems to be a <hi>derogating</hi> from <hi>His Honor Power</hi> and <hi>Dominion,</hi> which properly is in <hi>himself,</hi> and pertains to <hi>him alone,</hi> and not unto <hi>mortal man,</hi> which is to give <hi>Laws</hi> to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science,</hi> and to exercise it in all cases of <hi>Religion</hi> respecting <hi>his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, Duty</hi> and <hi>Service,</hi> and to <hi>perswade</hi> mens <hi>Consciences</hi> by his <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> to follow him, and observe <hi>all things</hi> which he requires in <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Worship:</hi> This <hi>Power</hi> is onely proper to <hi>God</hi> alone, and to him pertaineth, and to no other: And therefore for any <hi>man,</hi> or <hi>earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Powers</hi> of <hi>man,</hi> to give <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Rules</hi> to <hi>Conscience,</hi> and to <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose</hi> upon <hi>men</hi> in the <hi>matters</hi> of <hi>God's VVorship,</hi> forcing <hi>conformity</hi> in <hi>spiritual exercises,</hi> by <hi>violent commands,</hi> upon <hi>forfeitures</hi> and <hi>pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ishments,</hi> seems to be, and <hi>really</hi> is, an <hi>assuming</hi> and <hi>presuming</hi> upon <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Authority,</hi> which belongs onely to him, and tends to rob him of the same, and is an entrenching upon his <hi>Soveraignty,</hi> and and is wholly <hi>unrighteous,</hi> and inasmuch as it is a sitting in the <hi>Seat</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and forcing the <hi>Exercise</hi> of <hi>VVorship,</hi> and <hi>intruding</hi> upon his <hi>blessed Priviledge,</hi> and a <hi>presuming</hi> into his <hi>Authority,</hi> which he commits to no <hi>man,</hi> a robbing him of his <hi>Honor</hi> and <hi>Spiritual Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion:</hi> Therefore to <hi>impose</hi> in <hi>matters Religious,</hi> is <hi>unrighteous</hi> on their parts that do practice it. And</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is <hi>unrighteous</hi> because it is <hi>contrary</hi> to the <hi>Command</hi> of <hi>God, Do ye to others as ye would be done unto;</hi> but this <hi>imposing</hi> in <hi>matters</hi> of <hi>Worship,</hi> is a <hi>practise</hi> done by <hi>others,</hi> which <hi>others</hi> would not be <hi>done unto by any,</hi> and therefore 'tis <hi>unrighteous;</hi> for no one <hi>Sect</hi> or <hi>sort</hi> of <hi>Christians,</hi> would be <hi>imposed</hi> upon in that <hi>case</hi> by any <hi>others,</hi> not <hi>forced</hi> and <hi>compelled</hi> by <hi>outward violence,</hi> against their <hi>judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> and <hi>Consciences,</hi> unto such a <hi>Conformity</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Worship,</hi> to do thus is not to <hi>love a man's neighbour as himself,</hi> nor <hi>to do to all men, as men would be done unto;</hi> for if at any time and place the <hi>Papists</hi> (so called) <hi>impose</hi> upon the <hi>Protestants</hi> (so called) in this case, of <hi>forcing</hi> them unto <hi>Conformity</hi> or <hi>persecuting</hi> them about <hi>Religion,</hi> 'tis cried out against by such as are so <hi>imposed</hi> upon, to be <hi>tyranny, oppression,</hi> and <hi>exacting unrighteously;</hi> and thus every Sect
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:199695:9"/> of Christians cries out against others, that do <hi>impose</hi> upon them by <hi>force,</hi> in things <hi>religious, contrary</hi> to their <hi>judgments</hi> and <hi>consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,</hi> each sort when they suffer saith of others, they are <hi>unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> in such <hi>impositions,</hi> though many cannot see it to be <hi>unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> in themselves, when they have the <hi>opportunity</hi> to do it, and doth <hi>impose</hi> upon others; but this is where <hi>self-advantage</hi> kills and choaks the <hi>witness of God,</hi> though however in it self <hi>imposing</hi> as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid in <hi>religious matters,</hi> is <hi>contrary</hi> to the <hi>holy Law</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and a <hi>doing to others</hi> as men would not be <hi>done unto by others,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'tis <hi>unrighteous,</hi> both before <hi>God</hi> and all <hi>just men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. It is <hi>unrighteous</hi> to <hi>impose worship</hi> by <hi>force,</hi> because it is an <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercising dominion</hi> over men's <hi>faith,</hi> by <hi>force</hi> of <hi>outward power,</hi> which the <hi>Apostle renounces,</hi> and seems to <hi>forbid,</hi> saying, <hi>They had not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over mens Faith;</hi> and if the <hi>Apostles</hi> themselves had not <hi>power</hi> or <hi>dominion</hi> over men's <hi>Faith,</hi> that is to say, to <hi>command mens faith</hi> to <hi>believe,</hi> or <hi>do this,</hi> or the <hi>other,</hi> but as the holy Spirit of <hi>Christ</hi> perswaded their <hi>consciences</hi> inwardly; then no <hi>outward power</hi> of <hi>Kings</hi> or <hi>Rulers</hi> whatsoever, can justly or righteously cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge such priviledge as to have <hi>dominion</hi> over <hi>mens faith,</hi> by <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing</hi> upon them through <hi>force,</hi> which is to take <hi>dominion</hi> over <hi>men's faith,</hi> which is <hi>unrighteous,</hi> because it is <hi>contrary</hi> to the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and to the <hi>example</hi> of the Apostle <hi>Paul,</hi> inasmuch as it is <hi>exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cising dominion</hi> and <hi>lordship</hi> over the <hi>flock</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and not <hi>leaving</hi> them to <hi>Christ</hi> the true <hi>Shepherd,</hi> who onely ought to <hi>teach</hi> his <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> by his <hi>Spirit</hi> into <hi>all truth</hi> both of <hi>Doctrine, Faith</hi> and <hi>Worship;</hi> and hath not given <hi>power</hi> or <hi>authority</hi> to any <hi>Rulers</hi> of this <hi>world,</hi> to <hi>impose</hi> by <hi>force</hi> upon the <hi>consciences</hi> of his <hi>tender flock,</hi> nor to <hi>rule</hi> them in lordly <hi>dominion,</hi> exercising <hi>outward force</hi> upon them; but whosoever doth <hi>this,</hi> it is <hi>unrighteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. It is <hi>unrighteous,</hi> in respect of the <hi>fruits</hi> and <hi>effects</hi> which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways <hi>have,</hi> and ever will <hi>be produced</hi> by such <hi>imposition</hi> upon <hi>consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> in <hi>religious matters</hi> as aforesaid, (to wit) <hi>persecution</hi> and <hi>cruelty</hi> of men <hi>exercised</hi> in that <hi>case,</hi> which ever <hi>hath been,</hi> and <hi>will be</hi> brought forth in <hi>Nations</hi> and <hi>Kingdoms</hi> where such <hi>impositions</hi> are; for if we look into Ages past, what <hi>strife</hi> and <hi>contention,</hi> what <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> and <hi>bitterness,</hi> what <hi>warrs</hi> and <hi>bloodsheds,</hi> what <hi>dangers</hi> and <hi>mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs,</hi> what <hi>persecutions</hi> and <hi>cruelties</hi> have been brought forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men between <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Kingdom,</hi> between <hi>City</hi> and <hi>City,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:199695:9"/> yea between <hi>Kings</hi> and their <hi>Subjects,</hi> between <hi>neighbour</hi> and <hi>neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</hi> between <hi>brother</hi> and <hi>brother,</hi> upon this very <hi>unrighteous occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion</hi> of <hi>imposing</hi> upon <hi>conscience</hi> by <hi>force</hi> in respect of <hi>Worship;</hi> and every <hi>Nation</hi> and <hi>City</hi> at this <hi>day,</hi> is in the same <hi>danger</hi> of the same <hi>mischiefs,</hi> where such <hi>impositions</hi> are in <hi>force;</hi> and therefore needs must the <hi>occasion</hi> of these so <hi>unjust</hi> and <hi>unrighteous effects,</hi> which doth administer the <hi>reason</hi> of such <hi>contentions, warrs, persecutions</hi> and <hi>cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties,</hi> be <hi>unrighteous,</hi> and such is <hi>imposing</hi> in <hi>matters religious</hi> as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid: and this is partly <hi>manifest,</hi> and will be more and more through the world, That that <hi>Kingdom, City</hi> and <hi>Country,</hi> will not be <hi>free</hi> from these <hi>dangers</hi> and <hi>mischiefs,</hi> but will always be <hi>liable</hi> unto them, while this kind of <hi>imposition</hi> by <hi>force</hi> on the <hi>conscience</hi> is <hi>unremoved;</hi> and that which is the occasion of such continual <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent dangers,</hi> to destroy <hi>Kingdoms, Cities</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> is <hi>unrighteous;</hi> and such is <hi>imposition</hi> in the <hi>matters</hi> of <hi>Worship</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. It is <hi>unrighteous</hi> in any <hi>King, Prince,</hi> or <hi>Authority</hi> of this world to <hi>impose</hi> as aforesaid, because it diverts, confounds and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroys the end of <hi>just rule</hi> and <hi>government</hi> amongst men one over another, which is onely to <hi>rule well</hi> in <hi>outward affairs,</hi> and over the <hi>outward man,</hi> to keep that in <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>good order,</hi> and to be a <hi>praise</hi> to them that <hi>do well,</hi> and a <hi>terror</hi> to all that <hi>do evil</hi> in their <hi>outward man,</hi> this is the onely <hi>end</hi> of <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>rule</hi> among men in this world, to <hi>rule well</hi> over the <hi>outward man</hi> in things between man and man; but not to <hi>rule over mens consciences,</hi> and to <hi>exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise lordship</hi> over men in the <hi>spiritual matters</hi> of <hi>Christs Kingdom,</hi> this pertains not to the <hi>outward worldly government</hi> of men; and therefore whosoever do take it upon them, and thereby do <hi>oppress</hi> the <hi>conscience</hi> of any, by <hi>forcing</hi> in <hi>spiritual matters,</hi> doth <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteously,</hi> inasmuch as they do <hi>divert</hi> the end of their <hi>Authority,</hi> and use their <hi>power</hi> to another <hi>end</hi> then <hi>God</hi> hath appointed them; and while they should onely <hi>preserve</hi> and <hi>defend</hi> the <hi>outward man</hi> by good and wholesom Laws made for that purpose, they <hi>vex</hi> and <hi>oppress</hi> the <hi>inward man,</hi> even the <hi>conscience,</hi> by <hi>forcing</hi> upon it, and <hi>imposing</hi> through <hi>violence</hi> in the <hi>matters religious,</hi> which is contrary to the <hi>end</hi> of <hi>just rule</hi> and <hi>government</hi> in the world, and therefore is wholly <hi>unrighteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. It is <hi>unrighteous,</hi> because it <hi>effects</hi> no <hi>good end,</hi> nor <hi>begets-people</hi> into the true <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>worship</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> but on the contrary makes
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:199695:10"/> many <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> even through <hi>fear</hi> and <hi>terror;</hi> such <hi>Laws</hi> forcing <hi>Conformity,</hi> do make many <hi>hypocritically conform</hi> to such or such way of <hi>Worship,</hi> which the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> doth not perswade their <hi>Consciences</hi> of the <hi>truth</hi> of; nay it may be <hi>against</hi> their <hi>Conscience;</hi> and that (<hi>Imposition</hi> as aforesaid) which is the <hi>cause</hi> of this, is sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Unrighteous; unrighteous,</hi> because the <hi>End</hi> propounded by the <hi>Imposers</hi> (which is, <hi>to make people true Worshippers of God</hi>) is utterly <hi>frustrate</hi> and <hi>void;</hi> and none are made <hi>true Worshippers</hi> of <hi>God</hi> by such <hi>Imposition</hi> and <hi>Force,</hi> but many are made <hi>Hypocrites</hi> thereby, and <hi>sinners</hi> against <hi>God;</hi> for what any performs to <hi>God-wards</hi> by <hi>Force,</hi> and not of <hi>Faith</hi> (given into the <hi>heart</hi> by <hi>God</hi>) it is <hi>sin; For whatsoever is not of Faith, is sin,</hi> as saith the Scripture; and that which is the occasion of <hi>hypocrisie</hi> and <hi>sin,</hi> is <hi>unrighteous,</hi> and <hi>temptation;</hi> but such is <hi>imposing</hi> on <hi>Conscience</hi> by <hi>force</hi> in <hi>matters religious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. It is <hi>unrighteous</hi> and <hi>unreasonable</hi> to <hi>impose</hi> by <hi>force</hi> upon <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science,</hi> because it is the occasion of absolute extremity put upon many that are <hi>dear</hi> and <hi>precious</hi> to the <hi>Lord,</hi> even such an <hi>extremity</hi> as may <hi>force</hi> (unavoidably) the <hi>ruine</hi> of either <hi>Soul</hi> or <hi>Body</hi> (or both) in <hi>this world</hi> and hereafter. For, suppose such <hi>Laws</hi> be made for the <hi>forcing</hi> of <hi>conformity</hi> to <hi>command</hi> men to <hi>worship</hi> upon the <hi>forfeiture</hi> of <hi>whole Estate, Banishment</hi> or <hi>Death,</hi> which is <hi>contrary</hi> to the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and <hi>good Conscience:</hi> And if such <hi>Laws</hi> be not obeyed, and such <hi>Conformity</hi> made, but the <hi>Conscience</hi> kept clear to <hi>God,</hi> then the <hi>outward man</hi> in his <hi>Person, Estate</hi> and <hi>Family,</hi> is ruined in <hi>this world;</hi> and if such <hi>Laws</hi> be obeyed, and such <hi>Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> yeilded, contrary to <hi>good Conscience;</hi> then the <hi>inward man</hi> is ruined, and the <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Conscience</hi> wounded and grieved, because <hi>God</hi> is <hi>offended,</hi> and <hi>Christ</hi> is <hi>denied,</hi> and the <hi>Law</hi> of men obeyed, rather then the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> and this is by an <hi>Extremity,</hi> occasion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed through <hi>imposed force</hi> in the <hi>cases</hi> of <hi>Conscience,</hi> by <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>men:</hi> And that which is the occasion of such <hi>ruine</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction</hi> to the <hi>Souls</hi> and <hi>Bodies</hi> of such as <hi>fear</hi> the <hi>Lord,</hi> is an <hi>unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous thing,</hi> which administers that <hi>woful extremity,</hi> To <hi>deny God,</hi> and so to be liable to his <hi>Wrath</hi> and <hi>Judgements;</hi> or to deny the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> of <hi>men,</hi> and so to be liable to <hi>destruction</hi> of <hi>Person</hi> and <hi>Estate</hi> in <hi>this world;</hi> and such is <hi>imposing</hi> of <hi>Worship.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. It is <hi>unrighteous</hi> and <hi>unreasonable,</hi> because it may <hi>destroy</hi> the <hi>faith</hi> of some, even of <hi>such</hi> upon whom <hi>Imposition</hi> is laid, against
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:199695:10"/> their pure <hi>Consciences:</hi> For suppose a <hi>Person</hi> (or <hi>People</hi>) being <hi>truly</hi> perswaded by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> in the true way of <hi>Religion</hi> &amp; <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> having therein true Peace with <hi>God</hi> in a <hi>clean conscience,</hi> and by <hi>force</hi> of <hi>Law,</hi> and through <hi>cruel imposition,</hi> should be <hi>forced</hi> from that way of <hi>Worship</hi> which they have had peace with <hi>God</hi> in, and which the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> perswaded them of the truth of, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to such a way of <hi>worship</hi> which they could not have peace with <hi>God</hi> in, nor the <hi>comfort</hi> of his <hi>Presence</hi> in such <hi>conformity</hi> forced upon them; this were certainly <hi>unrighteous</hi> and <hi>unreasonable,</hi> that a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (or a person) should be forced by <hi>laws</hi> from that way wherein they have <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Blessings</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> to that way wherein their <hi>souls</hi> are famished for want of the <hi>Presence</hi> of the <hi>Lord:</hi> Like as if a person of such a <hi>Calling,</hi> following the same in a certain <hi>City</hi> or <hi>Town,</hi> whereby he <hi>maintained</hi> himself in <hi>all</hi> good things, and want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>nothing;</hi> and yet the chief <hi>Magistrate</hi> of the said <hi>City</hi> or <hi>Town,</hi> should <hi>forcibly compel</hi> (by <hi>violence</hi>) the said person of so good a <hi>Calling,</hi> from that his <hi>Calling,</hi> (whereby he so well maintained him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in the World) and should <hi>force</hi> upon him to follow another <hi>calling,</hi> of which he could not <hi>live</hi> in the World, but by it he might <hi>perish</hi> and <hi>starve;</hi> Would not all <hi>reasonable men</hi> conclude, the same <hi>imposition</hi> of the said <hi>Magistratee</hi> upon the said <hi>poor man,</hi> were <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression, Cruelty, Unrighteous</hi> and <hi>Unreasonable:</hi> And the case of <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing Religion,</hi> as aforesaid, is the greater <hi>oppression</hi> and <hi>cruelty,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asmuch as it respects the <hi>immortal Soul,</hi> which is more worth then the <hi>Body;</hi> and the other respects but the <hi>Body,</hi> which is of less worth (with all that concerns it) then is the <hi>Soul,</hi> which is <hi>immortal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lastly, 'Tis <hi>unrighteous</hi> inasmuch as it is <hi>contrary</hi> to the <hi>Scriptures</hi> (of the <hi>New-Testament</hi> in the <hi>dispensation</hi> of the <hi>Gospel</hi>) which are before-cited, and <hi>contrary</hi> to <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Apostles</hi> Example in the <hi>Primitive Churches of Christians;</hi> and thus it is manifest, That <hi>impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing</hi> by <hi>force</hi> upon <hi>Conscience</hi> in <hi>Religious Matters,</hi> is <hi>unrighteous</hi> and <hi>unreasonable,</hi> and is not of <hi>Christ,</hi> but of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> as by <hi>plain Reasons</hi> is demonstrated. And now I shall in a <hi>few words</hi> shew the <hi>danger</hi> of <hi>imposing VVorship</hi> as aforesaid; and how <hi>dangerous</hi> it is to any <hi>King, Prince,</hi> or <hi>outward Authority,</hi> that are or may be the <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posers</hi> on the <hi>Consciences</hi> of men by <hi>force</hi> in the <hi>case</hi> of <hi>VVorship</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:199695:11"/>1. It is <hi>dangerous</hi> to <hi>cause</hi> the <hi>People</hi> to <hi>sin,</hi> to <hi>cause</hi> them to <hi>conform</hi> in <hi>appearance,</hi> when the <hi>heart</hi> is not <hi>devout</hi> to <hi>God;</hi> and <hi>this</hi> makes them <hi>Hypocrites: Dangerous</hi> to <hi>cause</hi> people to <hi>perform Duty</hi> to <hi>God wards,</hi> without <hi>Faith</hi> in <hi>God;</hi> and this <hi>makes</hi> them <hi>sinners</hi> against him, <hi>for whatsoever is not of Faith, is sin: Dangerous</hi> to <hi>cause</hi> some to deny <hi>Christ</hi> before <hi>men</hi> for the <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>this world,</hi> and the <hi>terrors</hi> of <hi>violent men,</hi> and to <hi>forsake</hi> that <hi>way</hi> which they know is of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and to <hi>follow</hi> that <hi>way</hi> which they <hi>know</hi> is not of him; and <hi>this</hi> is <hi>denying the Lord of Life,</hi> and a great <hi>abomination</hi> against him; and the <hi>cause</hi> of <hi>all</hi> this is, <hi>Imposing</hi> by <hi>force</hi> upon <hi>Conscience</hi> in <hi>matters Religious;</hi> and the <hi>reason</hi> of that <hi>cause</hi> is the <hi>Imposers,</hi> such as <hi>make</hi> and <hi>execute</hi> such <hi>force;</hi> and this <hi>danger</hi> all such are <hi>involved in,</hi> even the <hi>danger</hi> of <hi>causing</hi> people to <hi>sin</hi> against <hi>God,</hi> of <hi>denying Christ,</hi> of <hi>making Hypocrites,</hi> and so even in the <hi>danger</hi> of <hi>destroying souls,</hi> which is a <hi>desperate danger:</hi> Oh that all the <hi>Imposers</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> by <hi>force,</hi> would <hi>consider it,</hi> and look upon the <hi>danger</hi> which they are deeply <hi>fallen</hi> into, and involved in, by reason of <hi>such</hi> their <hi>impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing</hi> upon <hi>Conscience;</hi> alas, they are in the <hi>danger</hi> of <hi>destroying souls,</hi> of <hi>causing</hi> a <hi>Nation</hi> and a <hi>People</hi> to <hi>sin</hi> against <hi>God,</hi> and to <hi>deny the Lord of Life:</hi> And how <hi>great</hi> is <hi>such</hi> a <hi>danger</hi> even to be avoided of <hi>all,</hi> if they love their <hi>own souls,</hi> and not to be the <hi>occasions</hi> and <hi>cause</hi> of destroying <hi>souls</hi> by <hi>causing</hi> people to <hi>sin;</hi> and this danger <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Imposers</hi> upon <hi>Conscience</hi> are captivated in. And</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is <hi>dangerous</hi> to be a <hi>means</hi> to <hi>destroy</hi> that <hi>Kingdom, City</hi> or <hi>Countrey,</hi> and the <hi>Rulers</hi> therof, by <hi>begetting</hi> and <hi>nourishing Discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, Heart-burnings</hi> and <hi>Envying</hi> among the <hi>People</hi> one against another, and against their <hi>Rulers,</hi> because of such <hi>unrighteous Force</hi> and <hi>Violence</hi> exercised by <hi>imposition</hi> upon their <hi>Consciences: Dangerous</hi> I say, to raise into <hi>Contentions, Strifes, Broyles</hi> and <hi>Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed</hi> it self, in a <hi>Kingdom</hi> amongst <hi>People.</hi> And this is a <hi>danger</hi> vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently impending upon such <hi>Rulers</hi> as do <hi>impose</hi> as aforesaid; even a <hi>danger</hi> to <hi>ruine</hi> their own <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> and to <hi>ruine</hi> the People under their <hi>Dominion,</hi> by raising the People into <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents</hi> and <hi>broiles,</hi> through the <hi>cruelty</hi> of the <hi>Oppression</hi> of <hi>impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing Religion,</hi> and the <hi>Example</hi> hereof may be read in <hi>Nations</hi> and <hi>Countreys</hi> at <hi>this day:</hi> What <hi>discontents</hi> and <hi>contentions</hi> have arisen <hi>dangerously</hi> among People one towards another, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their <hi>Rulers,</hi> upon <hi>this Cause</hi> and <hi>occasion</hi> of <hi>imposing Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:199695:11"/> by <hi>force unrighteously;</hi> and 'tis a <hi>danger</hi> this day, that all the <hi>Rulers</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> are <hi>exposed</hi> unto, and deeply <hi>involved</hi> in, where this <hi>Cause</hi> of <hi>imposing Religion</hi> is extant in <hi>force.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. It is <hi>dangerous</hi> to <hi>impose Religion</hi> by <hi>force,</hi> because it must needs produce <hi>Oppression, Persecution, Violence</hi> and <hi>Hatred,</hi> in the prosecution thereof; and this is <hi>dangerous</hi> to any <hi>Kings, Rulers,</hi> or <hi>Governors,</hi> to be reputed <hi>Oppressors, Persecutors,</hi> and <hi>violent men;</hi> this is <hi>infamous,</hi> and of <hi>bad report</hi> amongst men, and <hi>abomination</hi> and <hi>wickednesse</hi> in the <hi>sight</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> for any <hi>Rulers</hi> upon-<hi>Earth</hi> to be <hi>Oppressors, Persecutors</hi> and <hi>cruel men;</hi> and such consequently must they be that are <hi>imposers</hi> upon mens <hi>Consciences</hi> in <hi>Matters Religious:</hi> And this <hi>danger</hi> all the <hi>Rulers</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> are in, that do <hi>impose Religion</hi> by <hi>force,</hi> even to render themselves <hi>infamous</hi> by <hi>Oppression,</hi> in the <hi>sight</hi> of <hi>men,</hi> and to render themselves <hi>sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> against <hi>God;</hi> and this <hi>danger</hi> falls upon the <hi>Imposers</hi> of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> because of such their <hi>Impositions</hi> by <hi>Force</hi> upon the <hi>Conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> of men.</p>
            <p>Lastly, 'Tis <hi>dangerous</hi> because 'tis of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and not of <hi>Christ,</hi> as before proved; and all that do <hi>impose</hi> by <hi>violence</hi> on the the <hi>Consceences</hi> of <hi>men</hi> in <hi>Religious Cases,</hi> are of <hi>Antichrist</hi> in so doing, and because thereof, liable to <hi>God's indignation</hi> and <hi>heavy wrath</hi> in <hi>this world,</hi> and <hi>hereafter;</hi> and 'tis <hi>dangerous</hi> to bring the <hi>Wrath</hi> and <hi>Judgements</hi> of <hi>God</hi> upon men that are guilty thereof for <hi>God</hi> will be <hi>avenged</hi> upon such his <hi>Enemies</hi> that exercise <hi>Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> and <hi>Persecution</hi> upon men for their <hi>Conscience-sake:</hi> And <hi>This</hi> is a <hi>danger</hi> unavoidable, which all that <hi>impose Religion</hi> are liable unto, even to be <hi>cut off</hi> in the <hi>wrath</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and to undergo his <hi>Indignation</hi> for all the <hi>reasons</hi> before-shewed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>These,</hi> with many other <hi>dangers</hi> are they involved in, that are <hi>imposers</hi> in <hi>religious matters:</hi> Therefore, Oh that the <hi>Rulers</hi> of <hi>this world</hi> would be <hi>wise</hi> now in their <hi>last day,</hi> and would <hi>consider</hi> the <hi>unjustness</hi> and <hi>unreasonableness</hi> of their <hi>imposing Religion,</hi> and the <hi>many dangers</hi> that attends the same. Oh that they would learn <hi>God's Counsel,</hi> and <hi>rule</hi> only for him in <hi>Justice, Mercy, Truth, Equity</hi> and true <hi>Judgement,</hi> exercising the same in the <hi>meek</hi> and <hi>lowly spirit</hi> of <hi>Jesus,</hi> among men, and over whom they are set to <hi>rule</hi> in <hi>this world,</hi> and would give to <hi>God Almighty</hi> his <hi>Due,</hi> and <hi>Right,</hi> and <hi>Priviledge,</hi> in exercising the <hi>Consciences</hi> of <hi>men</hi> by his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:199695:12"/>
               <hi>Spirit,</hi> in all <hi>cases</hi> of <hi>Christ's Kingdom;</hi> for it <hi>onely</hi> belongs to Him to be <hi>Ruler</hi> in the <hi>inward man.</hi> Oh that the <hi>Rulers</hi> of <hi>this world</hi> would give this <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Dominion</hi> unto <hi>God,</hi> and would from henceforth never more exercise. <hi>Lordship</hi> over <hi>Conscience,</hi> by <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing Religion</hi> through <hi>force,</hi> but would onely <hi>rule well</hi> over the <hi>outward man</hi> in the things pertaining to man, and would leave to <hi>God</hi> the <hi>rule</hi> and exercise of <hi>Conscience;</hi> Oh! then would it go well with them, and <hi>happy</hi> and <hi>blessed</hi> should they be in such their <hi>Authority,</hi> and <hi>peace</hi> should be unto them, if that they onely took the <hi>Government,</hi> (as appointed of <hi>God</hi>) over the <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man,</hi> and did not <hi>impose</hi> upon the <hi>inward man</hi> by <hi>force,</hi> in <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious matters,</hi> but committed that <hi>Authority</hi> to <hi>God:</hi> Then I say, should <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>blessings</hi> be unto them: But while it is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, even while they exercise <hi>Dominion</hi> and <hi>Lordship</hi> over <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science,</hi> as aforesaid, they do <hi>unjustly</hi> and <hi>unreasonably,</hi> and brings upon themselves <hi>many dangers,</hi> and are liable to <hi>contentions, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions, wars</hi> and <hi>many mischiefs</hi> in <hi>this world,</hi> and to the <hi>anger</hi> and <hi>wrath of God</hi> in the <hi>world</hi> that is to come.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Concerning <hi>Heresie,</hi> the Case stated. What it is in it self, and who a <hi>Heretick</hi> is, and who are the absolute true Judges of it, and what punishment pertains to such as are truly convicted of <hi>Heresie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. THere is such a thing as <hi>Heresie</hi> in it self, even <hi>many Heresies</hi> &amp; <hi>Errors</hi> abounding among the sons of men in the world at this day; and there was <hi>Heresie</hi> in the dayes of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> and amongst them, brought in by such as erred from the <hi>truth,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:199695:12"/> after they had once known the <hi>Truth,</hi> and received it; as ye may read, the <hi>Jews</hi> they cried out of <hi>Heresie</hi> in their time, which caused the <hi>Apostle</hi> to say to them, Acts 24.14. <hi>After that way which ye call Heresie, do we worship the true God of our Fathers.</hi> And the Apostle said (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.) to the Church, <hi>There must be also Heresies amongst you, that they that are approved of God, may be made manifest.</hi> And (2 Pet. 2.1.) it is spoken of some who should <hi>privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bring in damnable Heresies</hi> into the Church: By all which it is manifest, there was in the <hi>Apostles</hi> dayes <hi>Heresie</hi> and <hi>Heresies,</hi> as there is at this day, even many <hi>Heresies</hi> and <hi>Errors</hi> in the world, held, professed, and maintained by the <hi>Apostate Christians</hi> that are gone into the <hi>form of godliness,</hi> without the <hi>power,</hi> and are turned from the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and the soundness of his <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> into the formal profession of <hi>Religion,</hi> and of the words of <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Apostles,</hi> and among such are the <hi>Heresies</hi> and <hi>Errors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Heresie</hi> is somewhat believed and professed in practice of Worship, and in point of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Doctrine,</hi> that is either <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary</hi> to, or <hi>different</hi> from the perfect <hi>Truth</hi> of the <hi>Gospel</hi> of <hi>Christ;</hi> something (I say) held and practised in point of <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, Faith</hi> and <hi>Doctrine,</hi> which is not justly according to the <hi>pure Truth</hi> of <hi>Jesus,</hi> but either in <hi>whole,</hi> or in <hi>part, different</hi> from, and <hi>contrary</hi> thereunto; and whatsoever practice of <hi>Worship,</hi> or point of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> as is so held, professed, believed or practised, is <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie</hi> and <hi>Error,</hi> because it is <hi>different</hi> from, and <hi>contrary</hi> to (in <hi>whole</hi> or in <hi>part</hi>) the perfect <hi>Truth</hi> of the <hi>Gospel</hi> of <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> and because thereof it is <hi>Heresie;</hi> and such is <hi>Heresie</hi> in it self, <hi>different</hi> from, and contrary unto the <hi>Gospel</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> though as for the particular parts and points of <hi>Heresie</hi> in <hi>Worship, Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> which are at this day held, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed and believed among <hi>Apostate Christians,</hi> are so very many, that they would be too large here to ennumerate; but my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent intention is onely this, To shew at large what <hi>Heresie</hi> is in it self, and who is a <hi>Heretick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. A <hi>Heretick</hi> (one that is properly so) is such a person as hath sometime believed in the <hi>Truth,</hi> and made profession and acknowledgement of the way of <hi>true Christianity,</hi> and hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and held the <hi>true Faith</hi> of the <hi>Gospel</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and been
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:199695:13"/> in some measure united to <hi>Christ,</hi> and a <hi>Member</hi> of his <hi>Church,</hi> but is <hi>fallen</hi> and <hi>degenerated</hi> in <hi>whole,</hi> or in <hi>part,</hi> from the said <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>acknowledgement</hi> of <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> and the way of <hi>Christiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and hath erred from the truth of the <hi>Gospel</hi> once believed and received, and so is divided (in <hi>whole</hi> or in <hi>part</hi>) from the true Church of <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> and from being a <hi>Member</hi> of the same; and not onely so, but hath received also, and doth hold some false <hi>Principles, Opinions</hi> and <hi>Practises,</hi> either <hi>different</hi> from, or <hi>contrary</hi> to the <hi>truth</hi> of the <hi>Gospel</hi> before <hi>believed</hi> in, <hi>known</hi> and <hi>professed;</hi> such a man is a <hi>Heretick,</hi> (though <hi>generally,</hi> yet) <hi>truly</hi> described: Not such as are <hi>Heathens</hi> unconverted, who never believed yet in the <hi>Gospel,</hi> such who have alwayes resisted the <hi>Truth,</hi> and never yet were convinced of the way of the <hi>Lord,</hi> nor ever tasted of his <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> but have always been strangers to the <hi>Israel</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and Enemies to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Christ;</hi> such are not properly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Hereticks,</hi> though they do err in <hi>mind, heart</hi> and <hi>practice;</hi> but such onely as have believed in <hi>Christ,</hi> and professed his <hi>Truth,</hi> and been of the <hi>Church,</hi> and yet are fallen away from the <hi>perfect truth,</hi> into some false <hi>principles</hi> and <hi>practices,</hi> and are become <hi>unsound</hi> in <hi>Judgement,</hi> and <hi>erroneous</hi> in their <hi>Understandings,</hi> and have forsaken the way of <hi>Truth</hi> (in whole, or in part) and are corrupted, and lost their <hi>Love</hi> to <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>wayes,</hi> and are obstinate, and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened against the <hi>Truth</hi> (which once they believed) and with <hi>false Doctrines, Principles</hi> and <hi>Practices,</hi> do gain-say and oppose the <hi>Truth,</hi> and them that are steadfast in it: These are <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and truly so called; Men that have erred from the <hi>Faith,</hi> that have made ship-wrack of it, and of a <hi>good conscience,</hi> that are turned against the <hi>Lord</hi> and his People, and gain-say the <hi>Truth</hi> that once themselves have believed &amp; professed: These are <hi>erroneous men,</hi> and <hi>Hereticks,</hi> &amp; such <hi>Hereticks</hi> there were in the <hi>Church,</hi> &amp; among the <hi>Corinthians;</hi> and there were such who did <hi>creep</hi> into the Church, and privily brought in <hi>Heresies</hi> amongst them, as before is proved; And these <hi>Hereticks</hi> were such as had once been amongst the <hi>true mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> of the <hi>true Church,</hi> and been convinced of the true <hi>Jesus,</hi> and had sometimes walked with them, but were departed from them, and had forsaken the <hi>Truth,</hi> and received false Principles and Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and therefore they were truly nominated <hi>Hereticks;</hi> and all such at this day are truly so called: And this is the Description in general, of a <hi>Heretick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:199695:13"/>4. Now I come to declare who are the <hi>true Judges</hi> of <hi>Heresie,</hi> and <hi>Hereticks:</hi> Not every man can judge in this case in his own <hi>thoughts, imaginations</hi> and <hi>suppositions,</hi> who are <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and who are guilty of <hi>Heresie,</hi> though it hath been the practice for many generations amongst the <hi>Apostate Christians</hi> to reproach, traduce and accuse one another to be <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and each sort and sect of <hi>false Christians,</hi> to judge, censure and condemn others that are not of their <hi>Judgement</hi> and <hi>Opinion,</hi> but <hi>different</hi> from them, to be <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks</hi> and <hi>Erroneous;</hi> and this hath been usual among many; but this is not the <hi>true Judgement,</hi> nor the way to try and judge truly who <hi>Hereticks</hi> are, by one <hi>sect</hi> and <hi>sort</hi> slandering and and accusing others to be such, because they have not <hi>conformed</hi> to their Way and Principles, but been different from them; <hi>true Judgement</hi> hath not been brought forth in <hi>this case,</hi> on <hi>this wise,</hi> but rather <hi>Envy</hi> and <hi>Enmity</hi> hath judged, and <hi>men's thoughts, imaginations</hi> and <hi>jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousies</hi> hath <hi>falsly judged</hi> in <hi>this matter,</hi> and no <hi>sound judgement</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined who have been <hi>Hereticks;</hi> for men have judged of one another by their <hi>private jealousies</hi> and <hi>evil conceivings,</hi> and censu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured one another to be <hi>Hereticks,</hi> without the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>sound dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning,</hi> and <hi>just Judgement;</hi> and all that <hi>Judgement</hi> brought forth in that <hi>case,</hi> without the <hi>infallible Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> which is onely <hi>true Discerner</hi> and <hi>Judge</hi> in the matter, hath been <hi>false Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and men hath judged one another <hi>falsly</hi> upon <hi>envy</hi> and <hi>evil suppositions,</hi> and without the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the <hi>Lord;</hi> and it hath often happened by reason hereof, That such <hi>so judged</hi> for <hi>Hereticks</hi> have been more righteous, and more in the truth, then they that have <hi>so judged</hi> them; and the <hi>Judges</hi> have been more out of the truth, and more <hi>Hereticks</hi> themselves, then they whom they have <hi>falsly judged:</hi> And this might be made appear through several <hi>Times</hi> and <hi>Ages</hi> since the Apostles dayes, among the <hi>false Christians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. None are able to discern of <hi>Heresie,</hi> nor to <hi>try</hi> and <hi>judge justly</hi> who are <hi>Hereticks,</hi> none but they (I say) that have the <hi>infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in them, to guide them, and have <hi>infallibility</hi> and <hi>perfect certainty</hi> of <hi>Judgement</hi> and <hi>Knowledge</hi> in that case of <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie;</hi> none else are rightly able to judge who are <hi>Hereticks,</hi> but such (I say) as have the <hi>infallible Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and are <hi>infallible</hi> and <hi>certain</hi> in their <hi>Judgements; These onely,</hi> and none <hi>else,</hi> are able to <hi>judge,</hi> they onely are <hi>competent Judges</hi> in <hi>this case</hi> of <hi>Heresie,</hi> and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:199695:14"/> who are <hi>Hereticks;</hi> and if any judge in that Case, it is but out of <hi>Envy</hi> and <hi>Enmity,</hi> and in the <hi>evil Suppositions</hi> and <hi>Conceivings,</hi> as aforesaid, and must needs be <hi>false</hi> and <hi>unjust Judgement,</hi> if they have not the <hi>infallible Spirit</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>infallibility</hi> of <hi>Judgement</hi> to discern by, and determine with in that Case; for no man nor men, may, or can justly judge another in the matter of <hi>Heresie,</hi> as a <hi>Heretick,</hi> by their own <hi>thoughts</hi> or <hi>suppositions,</hi> out of their <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,</hi> and for their <hi>self-Interests;</hi> but the <hi>Judgement</hi> in that matter must be <hi>just, equal, holy</hi> and <hi>true,</hi> and onely by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> which is <hi>infallible,</hi> and gives <hi>infallibility</hi> of <hi>judgement</hi> and <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning</hi> into all cases and things; for it was <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> and his <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles,</hi> and the <hi>Saints</hi> that had the <hi>infallible Spirit</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility</hi> of <hi>judgement,</hi> that could onely <hi>judge justly</hi> of such things, who were <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and who were not; and it was not the <hi>Jews</hi> nor <hi>Pharisees</hi> that could <hi>justly discern</hi> or <hi>judge</hi> in <hi>God's Spiritual mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters;</hi> but they alwayes judged of <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Apostles,</hi> and of the things pertaining to the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>God, falsly</hi> and <hi>unjustly</hi> in their <hi>evil suppositions</hi> and <hi>envy;</hi> and this was because they had not the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Spirit</hi> of <hi>Judgement,</hi> nor the <hi>certain, infallible knowledge</hi> and <hi>discerning</hi> of <hi>different things</hi> in <hi>spiritual Cases;</hi> and so it is now at this day amongst them called <hi>Christians;</hi> there is none can <hi>discern truly,</hi> nor <hi>judge justly</hi> what <hi>Heresie</hi> is, nor who is a <hi>Heretick,</hi> but such as are guided by the <hi>infallible Spirit</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and have <hi>infallibility</hi> of <hi>Judgement;</hi> nor none can make Laws whereby justly to judge of <hi>Heresie</hi> and <hi>Hereticks,</hi> but them who have the same <hi>infallible spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> guiding them, and have received <hi>infallibility</hi> of <hi>Judgement:</hi> So both the Law-makers, and the <hi>Judges</hi> of the Law, must be <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible</hi> in <hi>knowledge</hi> and <hi>judgement</hi> in this case of <hi>Heresie,</hi> otherwise the <hi>Law</hi> made for that purpose, and the <hi>Judgement</hi> given by that <hi>Law,</hi> are both <hi>false</hi> and <hi>unjust,</hi> and not according to <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Spirit,</hi> but are to be <hi>justly judged</hi> and <hi>condemned</hi> of the <hi>Lord God,</hi> in his <hi>day</hi> and <hi>season.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Now it remains to be enquired into, whether there is any punishment pertaining to <hi>Hereticks</hi> as such, for such <hi>Heresies</hi> held by them: Being first convicted truly thereof, as aforesaid, by the <hi>true Church</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> in whom there is <hi>infallibility</hi> of <hi>judgement, knowledge</hi> and <hi>discerning</hi> in that case; for in the <hi>true Church</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> doth <hi>infallibility</hi> of <hi>true Judgement</hi> and <hi>Knowledge</hi> dwell, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:199695:14"/> every <hi>true Member</hi> of the <hi>true Church,</hi> hath its particular measure of the <hi>infallible Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> whereby he is certainly perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the way of Truth in which he walks, and knows and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves the <hi>infallibility</hi> of the <hi>Truth</hi> he professeth, and is certain and secure of the way of his peace and assurance in <hi>God,</hi> which he hath received and believed; and also hath <hi>certainty</hi> and <hi>infallibility</hi> of <hi>judgement,</hi> and <hi>discerning</hi> who are out of the <hi>Truth,</hi> and in the way of <hi>Error,</hi> and are <hi>Hereticks;</hi> such are infallibly known and discer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>true Church</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and by every <hi>Member</hi> of the same, according to his measure of the same <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Gift</hi> of <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Discerning</hi> by it: And to such as are <hi>so</hi> convicted by the <hi>infallible Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> for <hi>such</hi> their <hi>Heresies,</hi> there is a Punishment pertaining; for <hi>Hereticks</hi> were to be punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the <hi>Apostles</hi> dayes, according to <hi>Paul's</hi> Instructions, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5 which was, <hi>That such a one as had erred from the Truth which once he knew, should be delivered up unto Satan for the destruction of his Flesh, that the Spirit might be saved in the day of the Lord:</hi> Here vvas a punishment described by the Apostle for this <hi>Heretick</hi> that had er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and gone from the <hi>Truth,</hi> and acted against it, though once he believed in it, and knevv it. And again <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.10. he exhorts and advises, That a man that is a <hi>Heretick,</hi> after the first and second admonition should be vvholly rejected, and turned avvay from, and judged vvith the Holy Spirit of God.</p>
            <p>And thus it is clear, there is such a thing as dealing vvith men that are <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and punishing them for such their <hi>Heresies,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Apostle</hi>'s <hi>Doctrines</hi> and <hi>Instructions:</hi> And vvithout all controversie, such as do err from the <hi>Faith</hi> vvhich once they have received, and turn from the <hi>Truth</hi> in <hi>Principle</hi> or <hi>Practice,</hi> must not escape unpunished, but must receive the sentence of <hi>just Judgement</hi> from <hi>God,</hi> and from his <hi>Saints</hi> that continue faithful.</p>
            <p n="7">7. But what kind or nature this punishment is of, in what way and manner such as are <hi>Hereticks,</hi> may be, and ought to be punished, is doubtful to many, and is a case at this time to be enquired into; for that <hi>way</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> of <hi>punishing</hi> such as have been supposed to be <hi>Hereticks,</hi> as among the <hi>Christians</hi> (so called) for many generations; (to wit) the way and practice of <hi>burning, banishing, killing, imprisoning</hi> and <hi>afflicting corporally</hi> the <hi>persons</hi> of them that have been called <hi>Hereticks</hi> for their <hi>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resies,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:199695:15"/> and laying <hi>forfeitures</hi> and <hi>penalties</hi> on their <hi>bodies</hi> and <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states,</hi> as hath been the <hi>practice</hi> of <hi>Papists</hi> and <hi>Protestants</hi> towards one another since the <hi>Apostles</hi> days, this <hi>way</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> hath not been of <hi>God,</hi> nor by any <hi>example</hi> or <hi>precept</hi> of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> or first <hi>Christian Churches</hi> established in their days; they did not <hi>practise</hi> or <hi>prescribe</hi> such <hi>dealing</hi> towards them that were truly <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and were <hi>erred</hi> from the <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>truth</hi> of <hi>Jesus Christ;</hi> not <hi>killing, burning, banishing</hi> and <hi>prosecuting</hi> the <hi>persons</hi> of <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> this was not the <hi>way</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> among the <hi>primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Christians,</hi> they <hi>did</hi> it not, nor gave <hi>institution</hi> for the <hi>doing</hi> of it at any time; but this <hi>way</hi> of <hi>dealing</hi> towards <hi>Hereticks,</hi> in such <hi>cruel proceedings</hi> as hath been in <hi>practice</hi> for <hi>many ages,</hi> is of <hi>Satan</hi> and <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and is <hi>downright murder, robbery,</hi> and <hi>wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedness</hi> in the eye of the <hi>just God;</hi> while one <hi>sect</hi> or <hi>sort</hi> of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians</hi> (so called) have <hi>punished</hi> and enviously <hi>persecuted another sort</hi> different from them as <hi>hereticks,</hi> with grievous afflictions in <hi>body</hi> and <hi>estate,</hi> even unto <hi>death</hi> and <hi>banishment,</hi> this hath not been of <hi>God,</hi> nor true Christian-like, but of the wicked one, and cruelties and murders before the Lord; neither is the same proceedings at this day, in any part of the world, where they are extant, any just, legal, righteous, Christian-like way of proceedings according to Apostolical example; but is of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ,</hi> and of the <hi>wicked one,</hi> as I have said; And this <hi>way</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> of <hi>proceeding</hi> towards <hi>hereticks,</hi> hath been so far from <hi>ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting</hi> the <hi>return</hi> of any to the <hi>way</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> that have been <hi>erred</hi> from it, (as the <hi>end</hi> of <hi>proceeding</hi> towards <hi>hereticks</hi> should <hi>ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi>) that the <hi>way</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> of <hi>killing, banishment</hi> and <hi>persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> by violence, <hi>hereticks</hi> (so called) hath hardned men in their <hi>evil way,</hi> and made such as have been <hi>hereticks</hi> more bold, confident and obstinate in their <hi>way, heresie</hi> and <hi>errors,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that have been more righteous, and clearer from <hi>heresie</hi> then such as have so judged them, have been destroied by cruel dealing, and many others have been destroyed in their <hi>iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> and <hi>errors,</hi> by being <hi>so proceeded</hi> against; and thus true <hi>judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>justice</hi> in this case have been perverted and turned backwards, and because of <hi>ignorance</hi> and <hi>cruelty,</hi> the <hi>righteous</hi> have suffered <hi>unjustly</hi> as the <hi>wicked,</hi> and the <hi>wicked</hi> have suffered by <hi>unjust proceedings,</hi> and thus the <hi>way</hi> of <hi>righteousness</hi> hath not
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:199695:15"/> been <hi>known</hi> in the <hi>Earth,</hi> but <hi>error</hi> upon <hi>error,</hi> one evil upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother hath come to, one sin added to another amongst the sons of men in the Apostacy amongst the false Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians.</p>
            <p n="8">8. But the <hi>perfect way</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> in <hi>proceeding</hi> towards such as are <hi>truly Hereticks,</hi> so <hi>discerned</hi> and infallibly <hi>judged</hi> to be by the true <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> is this; Let such first be <hi>admonished, advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, instructed</hi> and <hi>warned</hi> again and again; to <hi>beware, return</hi> from, and <hi>renounce</hi> such false <hi>principles, doctrines</hi> and <hi>practices</hi> held by them, and this in the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> in perfect <hi>love,</hi> and in <hi>meekness,</hi> and in the <hi>wisdom</hi> of the <hi>Lord God;</hi> such, I say, as are <hi>erred</hi> from the <hi>way</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and from the <hi>faith</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> once received, into <hi>error,</hi> ought thus in the first place to be dealt withal, by the <hi>way</hi> of <hi>admonishing, instructing, warning</hi> and <hi>reprov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> that there may be a <hi>returning</hi> and <hi>repentance</hi> towards the <hi>Lord</hi> and his <hi>truth</hi> again from whence they have erred; And if such shall not receive the <hi>instructions, reproofs</hi> and <hi>admonitions</hi> of the <hi>true Church</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> then such <hi>hereticks</hi> shal be rejected and cast out, according to <hi>Titus</hi> the 3.10, 11. saith the Apostle, <hi>A man that is an Heretick, after the first and second admonition, reject, knowing that he that is such, is subverted and sinneth, being condemned of himself;</hi> here is the description of the <hi>punishing</hi> of an <hi>heretick:</hi> If he will not receive admonition after being given him again and again, but doth harden his heart against the <hi>Church,</hi> and against the <hi>truth</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and will not <hi>repent,</hi> but <hi>persists</hi> in his <hi>errors</hi> and <hi>heresies,</hi> and that after <hi>reproof</hi> and <hi>admonition,</hi> then he is to be <hi>rejected; rejected,</hi> what is that, but a <hi>casting out</hi> from the <hi>unity</hi> of <hi>Saints,</hi> a <hi>departing</hi> and <hi>absenting</hi> from such an one, and a <hi>depriving</hi> of him of the <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>comfort, joy</hi> and <hi>felicity</hi> of the <hi>Assembly</hi> of <hi>God's people</hi> and <hi>servants;</hi> a turning from such in Converse and Fellowship, and a separating from them, and judging them by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> and this is <hi>rejectiag</hi> an <hi>Heretick,</hi> and delivering him to Satan, according to 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5 4, 5, 6. <hi>When the Church</hi> (the Saints) <hi>were met together, with the Spirit of God, and the power of the Lord Jesus Christ, such an one as had erred from the truth, and sinned against it, and was truly an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, should be delivered unto Satan for the destruction of the flesh, that the Spirit might be saved; Delivering unto Satan,</hi> what is that? but
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:199695:16"/> to let him be cast out into the wicked world, reputing him as such an one, and that he partake not of the sweet and blessed union and fellowship of Saints in their Assemblies and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse with the God of heaven, in his Spirit and Life; not to be numbred among the righteous, nor a partaker with them in the holy Union of the Elect; to pass judgment upon him e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally, in the estate he is now in, having both <hi>erred</hi> from the <hi>truth,</hi> and <hi>rejected</hi> and <hi>despised</hi> the <hi>reproofs</hi> and <hi>admonitions</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and as such to give him up to Satan, to give him up to that Spirit that hath led him aside from the <hi>Truth,</hi> and hardned his heart against it; to deliver him up to it, seeing he refuseth to be reclaimed from it, and hath chosen to follow it rather then the <hi>Truth,</hi> let him be left unto, delivered up unto <hi>that Spirit,</hi> even unto <hi>Satan</hi> in the wicked world, let him be cast out thither among the unclean, and not reckoned among the record and line of the faithful people; and separated from, and cast out so, as he expresseth it, <hi>vers.</hi> 11. <hi>If any man that is called a Brother be a fornicator, or covetous, a rayler, a drunkard, &amp;c. with such an one not to accompany, no not to eat:</hi> and this is to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a Heretick to Satan, for the destruction of the flesh, and is the proper punishment of <hi>Heresies</hi> and <hi>Hereticks,</hi> according to the Apostles advice and precept; but not to <hi>kill</hi> or <hi>punish</hi> the <hi>persons</hi> of men by <hi>corporal afflictions</hi> and <hi>penalties,</hi> on <hi>bodies</hi> and <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states,</hi> for their <hi>errors</hi> sake, this the Apostle gives no Commission for, but that such as <hi>erred</hi> from the <hi>Truth,</hi> and walked contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in <hi>principle</hi> or <hi>practice,</hi> should be <hi>rejected</hi> and <hi>delivered</hi> up unto <hi>Satan,</hi> in the way and manner as before declared.</p>
            <p>Again, in <hi>Matth</hi> 18.16, 17, 18 it is signified by <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> to the self-same purpose, in these words, <hi>If thy Brother trespass, go and tell him alone; if he repent, forgive him; if not, take one or two or more with thee, and tell him again: If he still neglect to hear, tell it to the Church; but if he neglect to hear the Church, let such a one be unto thee</hi> (as hath offended and rejected reproof and admonition again and again) <hi>as an Heathen man and Publican:</hi> In which words of Christ is truly signified the right and proper way of proceeding towards <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Offendor,</hi> even that they be first again and again ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monished and reproved; and if they resist the same then to be cast out, separated from, and not enjoy the union and comfort of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:199695:16"/> Saints amongst them, but as an heathen man and publican; but here is never a word signified of laying <hi>corporal punishments,</hi> and <hi>burning</hi> or <hi>banishing</hi> of persons for their <hi>Errors</hi> sake; and though they may offend, no proceedings of this kind are authorized by <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> or his <hi>Apostles</hi> in their day, but in another way and manner, as I have shewed, is the proper way ordained of God to deal with <hi>Hereticks,</hi> according to the Testimony of holy <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> signified by <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Apostles</hi> in the <hi>Primitive Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. This is punishment according to the nature of the offence; for as the offence is <hi>spiritual,</hi> erring in the mind from the <hi>Truth,</hi> and a going astray from the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> in a man's own parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; so the punishment is answerable thereunto, even to be sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the <hi>Truth,</hi> and not to enjoy the <hi>virtue, peace</hi> and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> of it, nor to be partakers thereof amongst the faithful peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: And this is truly according to the <hi>Justice</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> whose ways are <hi>just</hi> and <hi>equal</hi> altogether, and hath appointed <hi>just rewards</hi> for <hi>transgressors,</hi> according to the nature and merit of the <hi>fact</hi> and <hi>deed</hi> that is evil; and 'tis <hi>righteous</hi> and <hi>just</hi> that men that sin against their own souls, should be deprived of the <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>comfort</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; that all that do depart from the <hi>Truth</hi> once known, and sin against the knowledge thereof, should be no more a partaker of the <hi>virtue</hi> and <hi>felicity</hi> of the same; and that they who offend the <hi>Lords</hi> people, and <hi>revolt</hi> from the <hi>union</hi> thereof, should be cast out from them, rejected of them, and not enjoy the <hi>blessings</hi> and <hi>peace</hi> with them; even that all they that will not hear the <hi>reproofs</hi> of the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> nor be drawn with the gentle <hi>movings</hi> thereof, should be <hi>judged</hi> and <hi>condemned</hi> with the same, and not inherit the <hi>assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> of the <hi>Saints:</hi> And this is <hi>God's Justice,</hi> That all that love <hi>Evill,</hi> and walk in <hi>Iniquity,</hi> and despise the <hi>Lord,</hi> should be cast out into the <hi>sinful world,</hi> to have their <hi>portion</hi> with the <hi>ungodly,</hi> and all the <hi>workers</hi> of <hi>Iniquity;</hi> and this is <hi>just punishment</hi> according to the nature of the <hi>Offence</hi> of <hi>Error</hi> and <hi>Heresie:</hi> for in my <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> (and I have the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>just Judgement</hi> in this Case) It is <hi>great puishment,</hi> and sufficient for a man that hath once <hi>tasted</hi> of the <hi>virtue</hi> of <hi>Gods Presence</hi> amongst his People, to be cast out from the <hi>feeling</hi> and <hi>enjoyment</hi> of that <hi>life, virtue</hi> and <hi>Assembly</hi> where it is enjoyed; this is <hi>punishment,</hi> and a <hi>wound</hi> to the <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:199695:17"/> for a person that hath been turned from <hi>Iniquity,</hi> and witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the <hi>peace</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> to be left in <hi>iniquity▪</hi> and to witness the <hi>wrath</hi> and <hi>anger</hi> of <hi>God</hi> daily smiting him in his <hi>spirit,</hi> and upon his <hi>heart;</hi> this is indeed <hi>great punishments:</hi> And to have the <hi>holy Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> in his people (now) to <hi>judge</hi> and <hi>condemn</hi> him, whom sometime it hath <hi>comforted</hi> and <hi>refreshed;</hi> and to be <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>united</hi> and <hi>separated</hi> from <hi>that Spirit</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> amongst the <hi>Saints,</hi> which once gave <hi>life</hi> and <hi>joy</hi> amongst them. This man <hi>thus judged</hi> and <hi>condemned</hi> by, and <hi>thus separated</hi> and <hi>dis-united</hi> from the <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>People,</hi> is punished and afflicted suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently for his <hi>Error</hi> and <hi>Heresie;</hi> even in his <hi>Conscience, Soul</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> he is wounded, grieved, pierced, vexed and punished, though yet his <hi>outward man,</hi> and his <hi>person</hi> be not <hi>corporally</hi> afflicted by <hi>punishments;</hi> but he is afflicted <hi>within,</hi> he is dealt withall by the <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in his <hi>conscience,</hi> he is <hi>separated</hi> into <hi>darkness,</hi> and from the <hi>light</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>Assemblies</hi> of his People; he is at a distance from the <hi>Lord God,</hi> and the <hi>spirit</hi> which should <hi>comfort</hi> him, doth daily <hi>vex</hi> and <hi>judge</hi> him; and the people amongst whom he should be saved, is he separated from, and cast out to <hi>Satan;</hi> is now amongst the <hi>sons</hi> of <hi>Belial,</hi> the children of <hi>wickedness</hi> and <hi>ignorance</hi> that must be <hi>condemned:</hi> And this man is now <hi>rejected</hi> of the <hi>Saints,</hi> that once was <hi>embraced</hi> of them, and thus he is punished; for it is the greatest <hi>punishment</hi> and <hi>vexation</hi> for a man that hath once tast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of <hi>God's love, mercy, peace</hi> and <hi>blessings,</hi> amongst <hi>God's people,</hi> and to be forsaken of <hi>God,</hi> and without his <hi>love,</hi> in his <hi>anger,</hi> in his <hi>judgement,</hi> and in the <hi>curse,</hi> amongst the <hi>wicked,</hi> without <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>blessings</hi> amongst the <hi>Saints,</hi> this is <hi>punishment</hi> indeed, from which the <hi>Lord</hi> deliver all his <hi>people</hi> that <hi>fear him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet notwithstanding this kind and manner of <hi>punishment</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains to <hi>Hereticks</hi> as such, most properly, and not to be destroyed in <hi>person</hi> or <hi>estate</hi> by <hi>outward penalties;</hi> this I only mean and intend, Where the <hi>Error</hi> of a <hi>man,</hi> and his <hi>Heresie</hi> in his <hi>mind</hi> and <hi>judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> doth onely extend to the hurt of his own <hi>soul,</hi> and against <hi>God,</hi> and not to the <hi>harm</hi> of his <hi>neighbours person</hi> or <hi>estate,</hi> in that case he ought onely to suffer as before-mentioned, <hi>To be delivered up to Satan, and to be rejected, &amp;c.</hi> But if his <hi>Error</hi> and <hi>Heresie</hi> do extend further than onely against <hi>God,</hi> and his own <hi>soul,</hi> even to the <hi>wronging, in uring</hi> and <hi>defrauding</hi> of his <hi>neighbours person</hi> and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:199695:17"/>
               <hi>estate,</hi> and <hi>outward wrongs,</hi> or <hi>evils,</hi> or <hi>violence,</hi> or <hi>visible mischiefs</hi> be committed, as <hi>Murders,</hi> or other the like <hi>visible crimes</hi> against men, to the injuring of others, then I forbid not <hi>outward external punishments</hi> to be <hi>corporally</hi> afflicted upon the <hi>person</hi> and <hi>estate</hi> of such a man; but it ought to be done, and that by <hi>Laws</hi> of men pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for the same end; even such a mans <hi>Error</hi> in such his <hi>wrong dealing,</hi> may justly and lawfully be punished with <hi>death banishment,</hi> or <hi>penalties,</hi> according to the deserts of the <hi>crime,</hi> if his <hi>sin</hi> and <hi>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror</hi> be against men, let men deal with him, and punish him accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly: If his <hi>offence</hi> and <hi>error</hi> be onely against <hi>God</hi> and his own <hi>soul,</hi> let <hi>God</hi> deal with him, and punish him by his <hi>wrath</hi> in his <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science,</hi> which one day will be executed upon all that err from the <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>tribulation</hi> and <hi>anguish</hi> shall be upon his <hi>soul</hi> that doth evil, as it is written: But it is utterly unlawful, and sin against <hi>God,</hi> for men to <hi>kill, burn,</hi> or <hi>banish</hi> men for the <hi>error</hi> of their <hi>minds</hi> and <hi>judgements</hi> in <hi>spiritual matters,</hi> while they do walk <hi>justly</hi> and <hi>truly</hi> (as men) in the things pertaining to men, and are not inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to the <hi>persons</hi> or <hi>estates</hi> of any, by reason of such their <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,</hi> but they onely <hi>sin</hi> and <hi>err</hi> against <hi>God,</hi> and their own <hi>souls,</hi> to the hurt thereof, and not man, by any <hi>outward punishments</hi> or <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> executed upon their <hi>persons,</hi> but <hi>God</hi> and his people in the way and manner of the <hi>spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> as afore declared, ought for such their <hi>Errors</hi> and <hi>Heresies</hi> to deal with them, and proceed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them in respect of punishment for the same.</p>
            <p>Lastly, These things are but said in general concerning <hi>Error</hi> and <hi>Heresie,</hi> how they are to be judged and punished, and by whom, and to manifest that there is <hi>Error</hi> and <hi>Heresie, Hereticks</hi> end <hi>erroneous persons</hi> in the world; for (as I have said before) it was not now my work to ennumerate the particular parts of <hi>Errors</hi> and <hi>Heresies,</hi> that are held in <hi>Principle, Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> in the world at this day, they are so many and large; but yet more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, thus I would in brief define <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Heresie.</hi> That man (whatsoever he be) is in <hi>Error</hi> in all parts of his <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctises,</hi> held and maintained by him in point of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Worship</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> especially that is not perswaded of the <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>verity</hi> of his way by the <hi>holy spirit</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and led, guided, and taught in the performance and practice thereof, by the same <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Jesus;</hi> if the <hi>holy spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> dwell not in him, and doth not perswade the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:199695:18"/> heart in the belief of the <hi>Truth,</hi> and teach, and lead the man in the practice of it, such a man, even that man errs, and is in <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror</hi> in all what he is, and what he doth, in point of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>duty</hi> to <hi>God-wards,</hi> and that because the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness</hi> is not the onely <hi>Leader</hi> and <hi>Teacher</hi> in the things profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed and practised, but either <hi>tradition, example</hi> of others, or <hi>custom</hi> of <hi>places</hi> and <hi>times,</hi> or something else besides the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> which onely perswades into the belief of <hi>truth,</hi> and teacheth into the <hi>performance</hi> of the same, and thus is <hi>distinguished</hi> and <hi>known:</hi> A man in <hi>error,</hi> that is <hi>erronious</hi> in his <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> if not <hi>taught</hi> and <hi>perswaded</hi> by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> in what he <hi>is,</hi> and in what he <hi>doth,</hi> he is in <hi>error,</hi> and in a degree of <hi>Heresie,</hi> erring in <hi>mind</hi> and <hi>judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>conscience,</hi> in <hi>principle</hi> and <hi>practice,</hi> and subject to <hi>err</hi> in <hi>all things:</hi> Now as for the <hi>case</hi> of <hi>Error</hi> and <hi>Heresie,</hi> as the matter hath stood (in <hi>distinguishing</hi> of <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Heresies,</hi> in judging of the same, and in proceeding with <hi>Hereticks</hi> in the manner afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said) for many <hi>generations</hi> in the <hi>Apostasie</hi> since the <hi>Apostles days,</hi> all this hath been <hi>wrong,</hi> and not in the <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus,</hi> but <hi>men, cases</hi> and <hi>proceedings,</hi> all have been perverted from <hi>truth</hi> in <hi>that matter,</hi> because the <hi>spirit</hi> of <hi>darkness</hi> and <hi>ignorance</hi> hath <hi>ruled</hi> (and not the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi>) in the hearts of men; and the <hi>Spirit</hi> that is not of the <hi>Father</hi> (which <hi>Spirit</hi> of the <hi>Father</hi> is onely <hi>pure, perfect</hi> and <hi>infallible,</hi> because it is of <hi>God,</hi> and can truly <hi>judge</hi> and <hi>determine</hi> in these <hi>cases</hi>) hath been <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Judge</hi> in this <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and men out of their <hi>envy</hi> and <hi>hatred</hi> one towards another, have judged one another to be <hi>erroneous</hi> and <hi>Hereticks,</hi> &amp; proceeded against them thereupon; and such as have differed in <hi>Judgement</hi> or <hi>Opinion</hi> one <hi>sect</hi> and <hi>sort</hi> from another, and would not conform to one another in their <hi>ways, practises</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> it hath been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon for all different sorts of men to cry out one upon another, and against each other, <hi>Heresie, Heresie, Hereticks, Erroneous persons,</hi> and the like, and proceeded against one another, <hi>men</hi> against <hi>men</hi> differing from them, and <hi>sect</hi> against <hi>sect</hi> contrary to it self, and especially that <hi>sect</hi> or <hi>sort</hi> of people that hath had the <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>Nations</hi> and <hi>Countreys</hi> in their power, could, and hath easily proceeded against all others dissenting, upon the recount of <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,</hi> to the destroying of many, absolutely through <hi>envy, hatered</hi> and <hi>prejudice,</hi> and not upon the <hi>truth, soundness</hi> and <hi>verity</hi> of <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:199695:18"/> in that matter; and this hath been common for many Ages; Sometimes (according to the occasion proffered) <hi>Papists</hi> have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed <hi>Protestants,</hi> and sometimes <hi>Protestants</hi> have destroyed the <hi>Papists</hi> on this account of <hi>Heresie</hi> and <hi>Error:</hi> All which proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings have been in the <hi>Enmity</hi> and <hi>Ignorance,</hi> and not in the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Life</hi> of <hi>Jesus;</hi> whereby it hath come to pass, that many men have been destroyed for the <hi>cause,</hi> of which they have been more <hi>innocent</hi> than they that have destroyed them: And thus by <hi>false Judgement</hi> and <hi>cruel proceedings</hi> in the matter of <hi>Heresie</hi> and <hi>Error,</hi> many have been destroyed unjustly, and the world filled with <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> about difference in <hi>Religious matters,</hi> and with <hi>Murders</hi> and <hi>Cruelties,</hi> upon the <hi>false Judgements</hi> of men about <hi>heresie;</hi> and this is weighty, to be truly considered, a <hi>case</hi> to be lamented and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for, by the <hi>righteous:</hi> Oh what strife (in the <hi>Christian World</hi>) hath been for <hi>Ages</hi> on this occasion, each sort of People <hi>exclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> against, and <hi>persecuting</hi> others as <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>seditious persons,</hi> onely for difference in <hi>Judgement</hi> in <hi>spiritual cases,</hi> and each parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular person (almost) raging with fury, and intending his <hi>Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours</hi> destruction, and onely for being <hi>contrary-minded</hi> in point of <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Worship.</hi> Oh! the view of these things, and <hi>woful effects</hi> produced in the world for ages in these occasions, makes my heart <hi>grieve,</hi> because of the <hi>destructions</hi> of men, yea of the <hi>destruction</hi> of many upon <hi>wrongful judgements</hi> and <hi>proceedings</hi> on these occasions: I am troubled, I am troubled; and ever since I have known the <hi>right hand</hi> from the <hi>left</hi> (in <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>matters</hi>) my <hi>soul</hi> often in the <hi>deep search</hi> of these things, hath cryed out, How woful are they! And when shall it once be, that <hi>these things</hi> shall be no more in the world, but that every man may sit at <hi>rest</hi> and <hi>quiet</hi> with his <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>way, faith</hi> and <hi>practises</hi> of <hi>righteousness,</hi> as his heart is perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of, and not be tossed with <hi>false Judgements, cruel afflictions,</hi> and <hi>hard dealing,</hi> because of his <hi>Judgement</hi> and <hi>Conscience</hi> in the <hi>belief</hi> and <hi>knowledge</hi> of <hi>heavenly matters:</hi> Thus hath my <hi>spirit</hi> been fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with <hi>zeal</hi> against these things; this <hi>imposing</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> by <hi>force,</hi> these <hi>proceedings</hi> of <hi>killing</hi> and <hi>destroying</hi> men upon the account of <hi>Heresie;</hi> these things my <hi>soul</hi> hath loathed, and I am <hi>weary</hi> of them, and my <hi>zeal</hi> is kindled against them: Oh! when will the <hi>Rulers</hi> of this world learn <hi>wisdom,</hi> and forsake <hi>false Judgement</hi> and <hi>Oppression!</hi> And when will it be that they will onely <hi>rule</hi> and <hi>judge</hi> for the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:199695:19"/>
               <hi>Lord</hi> in their <hi>state</hi> and <hi>compass</hi> of <hi>worldly affairs</hi> between man and man, in the <hi>matters</hi> of <hi>outward wrongs</hi> and <hi>injuries!</hi> And when wil they leave it to the <hi>Lord</hi> to be <hi>Judge, King</hi> and <hi>Ruler</hi> onely, in <hi>all</hi> the <hi>cases</hi> of his <hi>spiritual Kingdom.</hi> Then should it be <hi>happy</hi> and <hi>blessed</hi> unto men, unto <hi>Kings</hi> and their <hi>subjects,</hi> to <hi>Rulers</hi> and their <hi>People,</hi> and to all sorts of persons, if <hi>Judgement</hi> were onely ascri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed unto <hi>God,</hi> that he onely might <hi>judge</hi> and <hi>determine</hi> of these <hi>cases,</hi> and punish men according to the <hi>desert</hi> of their <hi>offences</hi> of <hi>error;</hi> then should it be well with them: But in the mean time, whilst men are <hi>judged</hi> and <hi>supposed</hi> to be <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on sentenced to <hi>death, banishment,</hi> or <hi>corporal punishment</hi> for their (supposed) <hi>errors</hi> sake in <hi>matters</hi> of <hi>Judgement</hi> and <hi>Conscience: Tribulation, misery, distractions,</hi> and <hi>woful consequences</hi> will follow upon that <hi>work,</hi> to <hi>Kings, Rulers</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> in every <hi>Nation</hi> and <hi>Countrey,</hi> and no <hi>peace, true comfort</hi> nor <hi>happiness,</hi> shall be in the midst of men. And this is the <hi>Judgement</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in him who hath obtained favour from <hi>God,</hi> to receive <hi>knowledge</hi> and <hi>understanding</hi> in these matters. He that can receive this, let him.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Concerning <hi>Antichrist</hi> and his Mysterie of Deceivableness; What he is in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and how he appears in the World; what his works are, and what his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, and where it is, and who are the Subjects of his Kingdom.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THese things are great <hi>Mysteries;</hi> and though in the <hi>world</hi> they are very much abounding, and extant through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:199695:19"/>
               <hi>all Nations,</hi> yet for the most part unknown unto the <hi>world,</hi> and not discovered among the sons of men, but <hi>secretly hidden,</hi> and <hi>veiled</hi> under <hi>false covers,</hi> and in much <hi>deceivableness</hi> dwelling and working upon <hi>earth,</hi> in the <hi>deep Mysteries</hi> of <hi>Iniquity,</hi> to the <hi>deceiving</hi> of multitudes of People, who are indeed of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> among whom he <hi>dwells, appears, rules, reigns,</hi> and hath his <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> and yet they know it not, nor do they dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern him in his <hi>ways</hi> and <hi>works,</hi> though they are under his <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>subjects</hi> of his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> such indeed is the <hi>Mysteries</hi> of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ,</hi> his <hi>hidden, false covered pathes,</hi> in which he <hi>works</hi> and <hi>walks</hi> amongst the sons of men in the world, that he easily <hi>beguiles</hi> and <hi>betrays</hi> men, and <hi>deceiveth</hi> them unto <hi>perdition,</hi> while yet they know not that they are <hi>beguiled</hi> and <hi>deceived,</hi> but think they are altogether <hi>well,</hi> and do <hi>well,</hi> and are in the <hi>way</hi> of <hi>salvation,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing led of that <hi>wicked one,</hi> and <hi>blinded</hi> by him, and are <hi>bewitched</hi> into the <hi>false faith,</hi> and <hi>deceivable pretence</hi> of <hi>goodness righteousness, holiness</hi> and <hi>sanctity,</hi> as if they were indeed <hi>members</hi> of the <hi>true Church,</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> of the <hi>Most High,</hi> and had a <hi>right</hi> to <hi>eternal life,</hi> and were the very <hi>sons</hi> and <hi>servants</hi> of the <hi>Almighty,</hi> when <hi>indeed</hi> and <hi>in truth</hi> they are yet in the estate of <hi>enmity</hi> against <hi>God,</hi> in the <hi>degeneration</hi> and <hi>bondage</hi> of <hi>corruption, unconverted</hi> and <hi>unsanctified,</hi> and <hi>sinners</hi> and <hi>ungodly,</hi> the very <hi>Children</hi> of the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> and <hi>servants</hi> of <hi>unrighteousness,</hi> and have no <hi>assurance</hi> nor <hi>right</hi> unto the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> to rest in his <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>glory;</hi> such (I say) is the working of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> that he appears to be in the world contrary to what he truly is in his <hi>own being</hi> and <hi>nature,</hi> and deceives men and people into the <hi>apprehensions</hi> and <hi>conceits</hi> of what they are not, even contrary to what they are in their <hi>present state</hi> and <hi>standing;</hi> even so <hi>deep</hi> and <hi>mysterious</hi> is <hi>Antichrist</hi> in himself, and in his <hi>workings</hi> among the <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That there is such a <hi>man,</hi> or <hi>spirit</hi> in the world as <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ,</hi> this is not doubtful, but confessed by all, and proved by the Scriptures; for the Apostle wrot to the Church, <hi>They had heard that Antichrist should come, and even now saith he are there many Antichrists come into the world,</hi> 1 Joh. 2.18. and also 2 Joh. 7. vers. saith he, <hi>For many deceivers are entered into the world, and this is a deceiver, and an Antichrist,</hi> &amp;c. and 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 2. the Apostle speaks <hi>of the man of sin, and of the son of perdition, that should be revealed in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:199695:20"/> the world, and should exalt himself above all that is called God;</hi> These, with many other Scriptures, do prove that there is such a thing in the world, already come into the world, and now dwelling and walking in the world as <hi>Antichrist, Man</hi> of <hi>sin,</hi> and <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>perdition;</hi> and as I said, 'tis consessed by all that there is an <hi>Antichrist,</hi> such a <hi>Man,</hi> or <hi>Spirit</hi> now extant in the world; though there are great <hi>debates</hi> and <hi>contentions</hi> amongst many cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Christians,</hi> what this <hi>Antichrist</hi> is, and who he is, some hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one thing, and some another about <hi>Him,</hi> and there is much difference amongst men concerning this matter, and 'tis the general way of people one sort to accuse another that are <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent</hi> from them in <hi>Profession</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> That <hi>ye and ye are of Antichrist;</hi> but this hath been for the most part in <hi>enmity,</hi> and in the <hi>spirit</hi> of <hi>wrath</hi> and <hi>contention,</hi> and is not from <hi>true judgment</hi> and <hi>knowledge;</hi> now therefore it remains to be made manifest according to the gift of <hi>grace, knowledge</hi> and <hi>understanding,</hi> what <hi>Antichrist</hi> is in himself, and how he appears in the world, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we have proved that there is such a thing as <hi>Antichrist</hi> now <hi>ruling</hi> and <hi>reigning</hi> some where <hi>amongst men,</hi> throughout the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Earth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Antichrist</hi> is not (as some suppose) a <hi>particular visible per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> upon earth, <hi>distinct</hi> and <hi>divided</hi> from all other <hi>persons,</hi> as if none besides such an one were <hi>Antichrist;</hi> but <hi>Antichrist</hi> is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an <hi>invisible Spirit;</hi> a <hi>Spirit</hi> I say, dwelling in persons, even in many persons throughout the world, which makes them all of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> or to be many <hi>Antichrists,</hi> according to 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.18. <hi>There are many Antichrists,</hi> saith <hi>John,</hi> whereby we know it is the last time; so that 'tis plain there are in the world many <hi>Antichrists,</hi> many <hi>men</hi> of <hi>sin,</hi> or many <hi>sinful men,</hi> many <hi>sons</hi> of <hi>perdition</hi> and <hi>ungodliness;</hi> not onely one man that is such, but many men in the world, even all such in whom the <hi>spirit</hi> of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist,</hi> or <hi>Antichrist</hi> that <hi>spirit</hi> dwels and walks, they are all An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrists, or of Antichrist, because of that spirit of Antichrist which doth possess them, and rule them in the ways of sin and death, in Idolatry and false ways, and in opposition to, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> the Lord of Life, even all the deceivers in the world, all that are erred from the <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and are not of the true Church, gathered into his <hi>Name</hi> and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:199695:20"/>
               <hi>Power,</hi> but brings another <hi>Doctrine</hi> than that of <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Saints,</hi> and truly confesses not in <hi>word</hi> and <hi>practise,</hi> unto <hi>Jesus</hi> come in the <hi>flesh,</hi> all such are <hi>Antichrists,</hi> and of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to 2 <hi>John</hi> 7. even all the <hi>Apostates</hi> who profess <hi>Christ</hi> and <hi>his Truth,</hi> and <hi>his Church,</hi> and are not in the <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> but in the <hi>form</hi> of <hi>godliness,</hi> without the <hi>power,</hi> professing <hi>God</hi> in <hi>words,</hi> but in <hi>works</hi> denying him, all such are <hi>Antichrists,</hi> by reason of that <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Antichrist</hi> which dwells in them, and into which <hi>Spirit</hi> they are leavened and moulded, and are <hi>one</hi> with it, and brings forth the <hi>fruits</hi> of it in the <hi>world;</hi> and therefore they are <hi>Antichrists,</hi> more than one, even many <hi>Antichrists,</hi> as I have said.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Antichrist</hi> in himself is the man of sin, the Son of Perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is indeed and in truth the very <hi>Devil</hi> in his <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>kind,</hi> and in his <hi>power</hi> and <hi>spirit,</hi> and of him, and yet not <hi>divided</hi> nor <hi>distinct</hi> from him, but is him (to wit, the <hi>Devil</hi>) as he is in himself; and he is against <hi>Christ,</hi> and wholly contrary to <hi>Christ,</hi> and brings forth <hi>fruits</hi> and <hi>works</hi> to the dishonor of <hi>Christ,</hi> and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poseth <hi>Christ,</hi> and is in <hi>all things</hi> of a <hi>contrary nature</hi> and <hi>quality</hi> to <hi>Jesus Christ;</hi> and he is called <hi>Antichrist,</hi> to wit, <hi>before,</hi> or <hi>against,</hi> and <hi>contrary</hi> to <hi>Christ;</hi> And this is <hi>Antichrist</hi> in himself, an <hi>Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> an <hi>Enemy</hi> to <hi>all righteousness,</hi> a <hi>perverter</hi> of the <hi>ways</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> a <hi>hater</hi> of <hi>all good,</hi> a <hi>despiser</hi> and <hi>persecutor</hi> of <hi>God's people,</hi> and indeed a certain <hi>spirit</hi> and <hi>power</hi> distinct, divided and seperated from the <hi>living God,</hi> and his <hi>Son Jesus Christ,</hi> and contrary in <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>quality,</hi> in <hi>fruits</hi> and <hi>effects;</hi> and there is no <hi>fellowship</hi> in <hi>any thing</hi> between <hi>Christ</hi> and <hi>Antichrist,</hi> but they are <hi>divided</hi> and <hi>sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated</hi> one from the other, <hi>contrary</hi> and <hi>opposite</hi> one to the other in all their <hi>ways</hi> and <hi>works,</hi> and in their <hi>kinds</hi> and <hi>natures;</hi> for (as I have said) <hi>Antichrist</hi> in <hi>himself,</hi> in his <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>kind,</hi> is the <hi>Devil,</hi> and no other; he is the <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>sin,</hi> the <hi>sinful man,</hi> that conceiveth and worketh <hi>all evil,</hi> the <hi>son</hi> of <hi>perdition,</hi> the <hi>son</hi> that is lost from <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>reprobate</hi> for ever; he that is fallen, diverted, and cast out from the <hi>Presence, Glory</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>Creator;</hi> he that is <hi>seal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> unto <hi>vengeance</hi> in the <hi>wrath</hi> and <hi>enmity</hi> against <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> as being <hi>contrary, irreconcilably</hi> to the <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>works</hi> of <hi>Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:199695:21"/>
            <p>This is said of <hi>Antichrist</hi> as what he is in himself, as that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <hi>spirit,</hi> and not of the <hi>many Antichrists,</hi> which are onely <hi>Ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel,</hi> retaining this <hi>one spirit,</hi> and <hi>members</hi> of him through his <hi>Power</hi> dwelling in them, and by which they are <hi>one</hi> with <hi>this Spirit,</hi> and <hi>one</hi> in <hi>action,</hi> and brings forth the <hi>works</hi> and <hi>fruits</hi> of it; for 'tis pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, some that are such in their <hi>present standing,</hi> even under the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> may be <hi>converted</hi> and <hi>turned</hi> from him, and <hi>changed</hi> into another <hi>nature,</hi> and so <hi>saved;</hi> but as for the <hi>Antichrist</hi> in himself, as such, he is the <hi>Devil,</hi> and sealed up in the <hi>anger</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> never to be <hi>redeemed,</hi> nor <hi>saved,</hi> nor <hi>changed</hi> into another <hi>nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Though <hi>Antichrist</hi> in himself be the <hi>Devil,</hi> yet his <hi>appearances</hi> in the <hi>world</hi> are <hi>divers</hi> and <hi>many;</hi> and he appears in <hi>outward</hi> and <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible actions</hi> amongst men diversly; sometimes he <hi>appears</hi> in the <hi>way</hi> and <hi>form</hi> of <hi>open prophaneness,</hi> by the <hi>works</hi> of <hi>men,</hi> in all manner of <hi>unrighteousness</hi> and <hi>iniquity;</hi> for <hi>all sin</hi> of what kind soever, in <hi>every appearance</hi> of it, is of the <hi>Devil</hi> and <hi>Antichrist,</hi> even all <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane wayes</hi> and <hi>work</hi> of <hi>evil men,</hi> loving <hi>drunkenness, whoredom, dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-dealing, envy, malice,</hi> and <hi>every evil work</hi> and <hi>word</hi> brought forth by the <hi>sons</hi> of <hi>Adam</hi> in the <hi>fall,</hi> are all of <hi>Antichrist</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> and is his <hi>visible appearance</hi> in the <hi>world,</hi> though sometime his <hi>appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> is in another <hi>way</hi> and <hi>manner,</hi> even in a way of <hi>seeming righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness</hi> and <hi>holiness,</hi> and in the <hi>profession</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> and <hi>Christianity,</hi> and pretence of <hi>Faith</hi> towards <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Worship</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Fellowship</hi> in the same, and <hi>forms</hi> of <hi>Godliness;</hi> as if <hi>Antichrist</hi> were a <hi>Saint</hi> and <hi>Servant</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> thus, and after this manner doth <hi>Antichrist</hi> appear in the <hi>world</hi> amongst men now in these <hi>latter dayes,</hi> since the <hi>Apostles</hi> time, in the <hi>Apostacy</hi> of <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity: Antichrist</hi> (I say) though the <hi>Devil</hi> in himself, yet hath he often appeared as a <hi>Saint</hi> upon <hi>Earth</hi> in the <hi>pretence</hi> of <hi>holiness, righteousness, worship</hi> and <hi>religion;</hi> such hath been his <hi>policy</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivableness,</hi> that he hath put on the appearance of <hi>Gospel, Doctrine, Ministry</hi> and <hi>Ordinances,</hi> and covered himself thereby, that he might the better <hi>beguile, entangle</hi> and <hi>deceive</hi> mankind in the <hi>form</hi> and <hi>profession</hi> of a <hi>Saint,</hi> and <hi>Member</hi> of the <hi>true Church,</hi> he hath put on the <hi>sheeps cloathing,</hi> hath made use of the <hi>Saints words</hi> and <hi>practices,</hi> and hath <hi>exalted himself</hi> in the <hi>Temple</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> as if he were <hi>God;</hi> shewing himself to be <hi>God,</hi> and hath been lifted up <hi>above
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:199695:21"/> all that is called God,</hi> according to 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 2.4. and <hi>Christ</hi> himself said to his Disciples, <hi>That there should arise false Christs, and false Prophets, and should shew signs and wonders, if it were possible to deceive the very Elect,</hi> Matth. 24 24. which doth signifie, that the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrists</hi> and <hi>false Prophets</hi> should come into the world after his prophecie, which are already come since that time; they should <hi>pretend</hi> to be <hi>Christs,</hi> and should <hi>shew signs,</hi> and should <hi>deceive ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> with the <hi>profession</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and <hi>signs</hi> of <hi>Godliness;</hi> and they should have upon them, and be covered with <hi>sheeps-cloathing;</hi> that is, with the <hi>Saints words</hi> and <hi>practices</hi> in <hi>outward appearance;</hi> but <hi>inwardly,</hi> that is, in their own proper <hi>nature, fruits</hi> and <hi>works</hi> should be <hi>ravening Wolves;</hi> that is, <hi>destroyers</hi> of the <hi>flock, Matth.</hi> 7.15. and the <hi>Antichrists</hi> which <hi>John</hi> speaks, 1 <hi>Joh</hi> 2 19. they were such as went from the Saints that were in the <hi>power</hi> of <hi>god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness,</hi> they went out of the <hi>true Church,</hi> and carried with them the <hi>form</hi> of <hi>righteousness</hi> and <hi>truth,</hi> and the <hi>profession</hi> of <hi>Christiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> but without the <hi>power,</hi> and had lost it, and were departed from the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and the <hi>spirit</hi> of <hi>Antichrist</hi> had possessed them, and now led them, and ruled them, and they were <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrists</hi> (to wit) against him, and contrary to him; and these were the <hi>false Prophets</hi> and <hi>Deceivers,</hi> that went out into the world and <hi>deceived</hi> it, and led many aside into <hi>error,</hi> and many followed their pernicious and hurtful ways, as <hi>Peter</hi> saith, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>vers.</hi> 2, 3. and <hi>Paul</hi> speaks of such, <hi>as had a form of godliness, but denied the power,</hi> and in <hi>words professed God,</hi> but in <hi>works denied him;</hi> such were the <hi>Antichrists</hi> and <hi>Deceivers</hi> in the Apostles days, and such they are at this time in the world; whereby it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest, that <hi>Antichrist</hi> often appears in the world as a <hi>Saint,</hi> as a <hi>righteous one,</hi> and the many <hi>Antichrists</hi> they have gotten the <hi>form</hi> &amp; <hi>appearance</hi> of <hi>Church, Ministry, Worship,</hi> and <hi>Ordinances;</hi> and thus they appear <hi>deceiving</hi> the world &amp; them that dwel there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, with the <hi>appearance</hi> and <hi>vain-shew</hi> of <hi>Faith, Worship</hi> and <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> without the <hi>Power of Godliness;</hi> for unto that <hi>Antichrist</hi> is an <hi>enemy,</hi> even a <hi>destroyer,</hi> a <hi>persecutor</hi> and <hi>gainsayer</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>works,</hi> and the <hi>power</hi> of <hi>godliness</hi> and true <hi>Faith</hi> brought forth by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> though to deceive the world he can trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form himself into, and appear as an <hi>Angel of Light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:199695:22"/>6. Again, so <hi>deceeivable</hi> and <hi>mysterious</hi> is, and hath the <hi>appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> and <hi>working</hi> of <hi>Antichrist</hi> been in the <hi>world,</hi> that he hath not alwayes dwelt in <hi>one kind</hi> of <hi>form</hi> and <hi>profession</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Righteousness,</hi> but he hath dwelt in many <hi>appearances,</hi> and removed out of <hi>one false form,</hi> into <hi>another,</hi> according to his <hi>opportunity</hi> and <hi>advantage,</hi> whereby he could <hi>deceive;</hi> and sometime dwelling in <hi>one form,</hi> with pretence of <hi>zeal,</hi> and <hi>performance</hi> of <hi>duty</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> he hath <hi>envied, persecuted,</hi> and <hi>destroyed</hi> many others in other <hi>ways</hi> of <hi>profession,</hi> more <hi>zealous, upright</hi> and <hi>sincere</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> than them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves have been in the other <hi>form;</hi> and by the <hi>colour</hi> of <hi>zeal,</hi> and <hi>performance</hi> of <hi>duty,</hi> hath <hi>Antichrist</hi> cloathed himself in his <hi>envies, persecutions</hi> and <hi>murders</hi> of <hi>others,</hi> as if he did not <hi>persecute</hi> nor <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose</hi> upon the <hi>Conscience</hi> of any, nor <hi>exercise</hi> that <hi>rigor</hi> (or <hi>justice,</hi> as he hath named his <hi>proceedings,</hi> though never so <hi>cruel</hi> and <hi>unjust</hi>) towards any, upon any <hi>tearms</hi> or <hi>account</hi> of <hi>wrath, bitterness, envy</hi> or <hi>cruelty,</hi> but <hi>zeal, duty</hi> and <hi>love</hi> to <hi>Religion,</hi> and to <hi>extinguish He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie,</hi> &amp;c. This hath been the <hi>pretence</hi> and <hi>cloak</hi> of <hi>Antichrist</hi> in his <hi>cruel</hi> and <hi>hard dealing</hi> with many men that have <hi>differed</hi> in <hi>principle</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> of <hi>Religion;</hi> he hath often shewed himself in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent <hi>form</hi> of <hi>godliness,</hi> so <hi>zealous</hi> and <hi>dutiful</hi> for the <hi>truth</hi> of his <hi>way,</hi> (though never so <hi>Idolatrous</hi>) against all that have <hi>opposed</hi> it, &amp; gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayed his <hi>form</hi> and <hi>vain shew,</hi> that he hath <hi>killed, slain,</hi> and <hi>exercised cruelty</hi> towards all that have been <hi>contrary</hi> or <hi>different-minded;</hi> and though this hath been brought forth by <hi>Antichrist,</hi> as he is the <hi>Devil</hi> in himself, and in <hi>down-right envy, malice, persecution,</hi> and <hi>wickedness;</hi> yet it hath been <hi>acted</hi> and <hi>effected</hi> under the <hi>Cloak</hi> of <hi>Zeal, Duty</hi> and <hi>Sincerity,</hi> and out of <hi>pretence</hi> of <hi>love</hi> to <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Church,</hi> and out of <hi>pretence</hi> of <hi>hatred</hi> against the <hi>contrary.</hi> Thus hath <hi>Antichrist</hi> (though the <hi>Devil,</hi> that wicked one, as he is in himself, in his <hi>own nature, kind,</hi> and <hi>proper sphear</hi>) appeared in the <hi>world</hi> as a <hi>zealous Church-Member,</hi> as a <hi>Saint,</hi> as a <hi>promoter</hi> of <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness,</hi> and a <hi>destroyer</hi> of the <hi>contrary:</hi> With these <hi>false covers</hi> hath <hi>Antichrist</hi> been <hi>cloaked</hi> and <hi>hidden</hi> from men, and appeared to be in his <hi>works</hi> and <hi>transactions,</hi> as a <hi>good man,</hi> as a <hi>lover</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>hater</hi> of <hi>iniquity,</hi> while in the mean time he hath been <hi>deceiving men,</hi> and <hi>destroying</hi> the <hi>innocent,</hi> and leading the <hi>world</hi> to perpetual <hi>misery</hi> and <hi>destruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:199695:22"/>7. Again, so <hi>deceivable</hi> hath the <hi>spirit</hi> of <hi>Antichrist</hi> been in the <hi>World,</hi> that he hath always put the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and the <hi>Name</hi> of his <hi>Church,</hi> and the pretence of <hi>duty</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Gospel, Doctrine, Ordinances, Ministry</hi> and <hi>Worship,</hi> upon whatsoever <hi>false way, feigned Worship,</hi> and <hi>deceitful profession,</hi> that he hath gone about to <hi>set up</hi> and <hi>promote</hi> in the <hi>world</hi> among men: I say, upon the <hi>worst</hi> and most <hi>Idolatrous wayes</hi> of <hi>superstition,</hi> and the most <hi>false, feigned, formal Worship</hi> that ever hath been in the <hi>world, Antichrist</hi> hath put the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> his <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Worship,</hi> upon them, and <hi>imposed</hi> and <hi>forced</hi> the <hi>belief</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> of much <hi>false Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, false Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>formal wayes,</hi> under the <hi>name</hi> and <hi>title</hi> of the <hi>true Christ,</hi> his <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Worship,</hi> and upon <hi>pains</hi> and <hi>penalties</hi> hath <hi>enjoined</hi> and <hi>commanded</hi> the <hi>belief</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> of such things, not as if they were of <hi>Antichrist, superstitious, evil, false</hi> or <hi>feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi> but as if they were of <hi>Christ</hi> altogether, and must be <hi>believed</hi> and <hi>practised,</hi> as by his <hi>Name,</hi> and under his <hi>Authority:</hi> Thus hath been the <hi>working</hi> of the <hi>Mysterie</hi> of <hi>Iniquity</hi> of that <hi>man</hi> of <hi>sin,</hi> the <hi>Antichrist,</hi> all the <hi>evil wayes</hi> he hath conceived and brought forth in the <hi>world;</hi> all the <hi>idolatrous Worship,</hi> and <hi>false Faith</hi> and <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and all the <hi>Cruelties, Murders,</hi> and <hi>unjust dealing,</hi> to the very <hi>destroying</hi> of the <hi>Saints;</hi> and all the <hi>unrighteousness</hi> and <hi>deceive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableness</hi> exercised by <hi>Antichrist</hi> in the <hi>world,</hi> hath put all this on the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and pretended <hi>Christ</hi> for it, as if it were <hi>indeed</hi> and in <hi>truth</hi> of him, and from him, when <hi>indeed</hi> and <hi>in truth</hi> it hath been <hi>contrary</hi> to the <hi>true Christ,</hi> and tended to <hi>kill</hi> and <hi>destroy</hi> him: Thus hath <hi>Antichrist</hi> the <hi>Devil</hi> been cloaked with <hi>false covers</hi> and <hi>deceitful pretences</hi> in his working among men; that <hi>wicked spirit</hi> hath falsly called the greatest of <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>ambition, decency</hi> and <hi>true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; covetousness</hi> and <hi>deceitful dealing,</hi> hath he stiled <hi>good Husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry,</hi> and <hi>prudent walking;</hi> and the most <hi>cruel</hi> and <hi>unjust Judgement,</hi> the <hi>oppression</hi> of the <hi>poor,</hi> and the <hi>grinding</hi> of the <hi>face</hi> of the <hi>inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,</hi> hath that <hi>Spirit</hi> falsly titled <hi>equal proceedings, justice,</hi> and <hi>according to Law,</hi> and the like: Yea, and the <hi>Persecutions</hi> and <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> that ever hath been acted against the <hi>Saints</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in all <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> though <hi>cruel</hi> and <hi>unrighteous,</hi> and of the <hi>Devil;</hi> yet all this hath <hi>Antichrist</hi> titled to be in <hi>honor</hi> to <hi>Christ,</hi> and for the <hi>destroying Hereticks,</hi> and out of <hi>Justice</hi> and <hi>Zeal</hi> for <hi>God,</hi> and such like; yea and the most <hi>grosse Idolatries,</hi> and most <hi>deceitful ways</hi> of <hi>Worship</hi> that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:199695:23"/> ever have been set up in the <hi>world,</hi> have been named after <hi>Christ,</hi> and pretended to be done in <hi>honor</hi> to him; and for his <hi>glory,</hi> and so forth, so <hi>deceivable</hi> hath <hi>Antichrist</hi> been in the <hi>world,</hi> and <hi>walked</hi> and <hi>wrought</hi> among the <hi>sons</hi> of <hi>men,</hi> in <hi>deceiving</hi> of them, that he hath used, and taken upon him the very <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Christ;</hi> and all his <hi>evil works</hi> of <hi>iniquity</hi> of <hi>all kinds,</hi> hath he put the <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> upon them, and so <hi>deceived</hi> the <hi>World</hi> by his <hi>false wayes, worships, doctrines</hi> and <hi>persecutions,</hi> through <hi>covering</hi> these things with the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and pretending his <hi>honor</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation,</hi> when as his own <hi>true property</hi> and <hi>nature</hi> is to <hi>kill Christ,</hi> and <hi>gain-say</hi> him. And <hi>this</hi> indeed is <hi>Antichrist,</hi> who under <hi>colour</hi> and <hi>pretence</hi> of <hi>worshipping</hi> and <hi>honoring Christ,</hi> doth seek to slay him. This is that <hi>Fox, crafty</hi> and <hi>deceitful,</hi> that <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>Sin</hi> that hath been <hi>exalted;</hi> that <hi>Antichrist,</hi> the <hi>wicked one,</hi> that hath decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the <hi>world</hi> for <hi>many Ages;</hi> but the <hi>Lord</hi> is now <hi>discovering</hi> him, and <hi>destroying</hi> him by the <hi>breath</hi> of his <hi>mouth,</hi> and by the <hi>brightness</hi> of his <hi>coming,</hi> according to the <hi>faithful promise</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in his <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> and <hi>Antichrist</hi> shall be <hi>discovered</hi> and <hi>destroyed:</hi> The Day of the <hi>Lord</hi> is at hand upon him.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Again, it hath been the <hi>way</hi> of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> that he might the better <hi>deceive</hi> the world, to transform himself into the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of the <hi>best way</hi> and <hi>strictest profession</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> and so to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move from one <hi>way</hi> and <hi>form</hi> unto <hi>another,</hi> as I said before, that he might the better <hi>deceive men;</hi> according as <hi>Paul</hi> writ, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>vers.</hi> 13, 14. for such are false Apostles, deceitful workers, transforming themselves into the <hi>Apostles of Christ;</hi> and no marvel, for <hi>Satan</hi> himself is <hi>transformed</hi> into an <hi>Angel</hi> of <hi>Light;</hi> by which it is plain, that <hi>Antichrist</hi> did <hi>change</hi> and <hi>transform</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and <hi>remove</hi> from one <hi>way</hi> to <hi>another,</hi> even till he <hi>appeared</hi> as an <hi>angel</hi> of <hi>Light,</hi> and in the very <hi>way</hi> and <hi>form</hi> of the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry</hi> of <hi>Righteousness;</hi> thus did <hi>Antichrist</hi> work and <hi>transform</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in the days of the Apostles, and ever since unto this day in all times and ages; for it hath been his manner and way, when he could no longer <hi>cover himself,</hi> nor be <hi>hid</hi> in such a <hi>way</hi> of <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> in which he hath sometimes <hi>dwelt</hi> and <hi>walked;</hi> but that his <hi>wickedness, cruelties, persecutions</hi> and <hi>deceits</hi> must needs be <hi>seen</hi> and made <hi>appear</hi> unto men by the <hi>Light</hi> of the <hi>Lord shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> amongst them; then he hath <hi>transformed</hi> into another <hi>like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:199695:23"/> and removed his <hi>cruelties</hi> and <hi>persecutions</hi> into another <hi>form</hi> and <hi>appearance;</hi> it may be into the <hi>very way</hi> (in the <hi>outward professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> of it) in which sometime the <hi>Lord</hi> hath <hi>dwelt</hi> and <hi>walked,</hi> and there hath he <hi>dwelt</hi> deceiving the <hi>world</hi> by his <hi>new form</hi> and <hi>appearance,</hi> and <hi>exercised</hi> his <hi>wickedness, cruelties</hi> and <hi>persecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> in some <hi>new way,</hi> having quitted the <hi>last form</hi> in which he <hi>dwelt,</hi> because he was there too <hi>publikely</hi> seen and discovered: And now in his <hi>new likeness</hi> into which he is <hi>transformed,</hi> he can plead the <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample</hi> of <hi>Saints;</hi> they did such things, and held such <hi>Doctrines,</hi> and performed such <hi>practises</hi> as now he is found in; and this did the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> sometime to <hi>Christ,</hi> he pleaded <hi>Scripture</hi> against him: And thus <hi>Antichrist</hi> can change himself into <hi>divers appearances,</hi> that he may <hi>deceive</hi> men: Well, but and if he be again <hi>discovered,</hi> and his <hi>cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties</hi> and <hi>wickedness</hi> made appear in his <hi>last</hi> and <hi>newest form,</hi> he can <hi>transform</hi> again into a <hi>more strict way,</hi> and <hi>zealous performance,</hi> even into an <hi>Angel</hi> of <hi>Light,</hi> as if he were indeed the <hi>true Christ,</hi> and were in the <hi>Truth</hi> altogether, and no man needed to doubt of the <hi>truth</hi> of his <hi>way;</hi> and then under that <hi>form</hi> being <hi>covered</hi> with <hi>more zeal</hi> then ever, with <hi>more pretence</hi> of <hi>duty</hi> to <hi>God</hi> then before, he <hi>blinds</hi> the <hi>world,</hi> and <hi>deceives</hi> them, and leads men to <hi>perdition;</hi> and though <hi>changeable</hi> in his <hi>appearance,</hi> yet is he in himself <hi>Antichrist</hi> still, in his own <hi>proper nature</hi> a <hi>Murderer, Destroyer,</hi> and a <hi>Fountain</hi> of <hi>Mischief</hi> and <hi>Evil.</hi> The <hi>truth</hi> of this is <hi>plain,</hi> if it be consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed throughout the course of <hi>Scriptures</hi> in <hi>Generations</hi> past, and <hi>transactions</hi> of <hi>time;</hi> as in the <hi>Prophets</hi> dayes of old, this <hi>Spirit</hi> (which is no other but the <hi>Devil</hi>) sometimes <hi>opposed, gain-sayed,</hi> and <hi>persecuted</hi> the <hi>Prophets, reproached</hi> them, and <hi>withstood</hi> them, and <hi>imprisoned</hi> them, and <hi>killed</hi> them: And sometimes we find the <hi>same spirit</hi> transformed it self into the <hi>way</hi> of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and acted by some <hi>deceivers</hi> and <hi>false Prophets</hi> in the same <hi>words</hi> and <hi>practices,</hi> which the <hi>true Prophets</hi> had said and done; and as the <hi>true Prophets</hi> used their <hi>tongues,</hi> and said, <hi>The Lord saith it;</hi> so the <hi>false Prophets</hi> (in whom the <hi>Devil</hi> was <hi>transformed</hi>) they used their <hi>tongues,</hi> and said, <hi>The Lord saith it</hi> (also,) when <hi>God</hi> had not <hi>spoken</hi> to them: So here was this <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Antichrist changing</hi> and <hi>trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming</hi> himself, that he might the better deceive. Also, in the dayes of <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Apostles,</hi> the <hi>Devil</hi> and <hi>Antichrist</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:199695:24"/> against them, and <hi>persecuted</hi> them, and <hi>killed</hi> them and used <hi>cruelty</hi> and <hi>injustice</hi> towards them; and (as before I said) this was done to <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Apostles,</hi> by the <hi>wicked Jews,</hi> under <hi>colour</hi> and <hi>pretence</hi> of <hi>love</hi> to their <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>zeal</hi> for their <hi>Law,</hi> and for the <hi>honor</hi> of their <hi>Ordinances</hi> and <hi>Priesthood,</hi> which they suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Apostles</hi> made void. Which shews, that the <hi>Devil</hi> and <hi>Antichrist</hi> appears in the <hi>world</hi> as a <hi>good man,</hi> as a <hi>lover</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and his <hi>Laws,</hi> and the like. Well, but though the <hi>envious men,</hi> and <hi>wicked persons,</hi> (through the <hi>spirit</hi> of the <hi>Devil</hi>) did for some time <hi>oppose, gainsay,</hi> and <hi>persecute Christ</hi> and his <hi>Apostles,</hi> yet the same <hi>Spirit</hi> (possibly some of the <hi>same persons</hi>) trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed into the <hi>profession</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and into the <hi>profession</hi> of the <hi>words</hi> and <hi>works</hi> of <hi>Him</hi> and his <hi>Apostles:</hi> For we find <hi>envious men,</hi> and <hi>wicked men,</hi> such as had <hi>persecuted Christ,</hi> and <hi>kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> him, were gotten to preach him in <hi>words,</hi> and had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and taken upon them the <hi>Form</hi> of <hi>Christ's Doctrine,</hi> and preached him out of <hi>Envy,</hi> and for <hi>self-ends,</hi> and the like: So that 'tis plain, The same <hi>Spirit</hi> that sometime <hi>opposed</hi> and <hi>perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted</hi> the <hi>Prophets, Christ</hi> and his <hi>Apostles,</hi> other times was trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed into the <hi>profession</hi> of the <hi>Prophets, Christ</hi> and his <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles</hi> words: And this is the way of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> to deceive men upon <hi>Earth,</hi> and to lead them to <hi>perdition:</hi> For when the <hi>Devil</hi> and <hi>Antichrist</hi> perceives that his <hi>Envy, Malice</hi> and <hi>Cruelty</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not prevail to subdue and keep under the <hi>Way</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> of <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> as it appears in the <hi>world,</hi> then he transforms into the <hi>likeness</hi> and <hi>formal appearance</hi> of the way of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and his <hi>Truth;</hi> and when the <hi>Devil</hi> cannot <hi>kill Christ</hi> so, but that <hi>Christ</hi> will <hi>rise again, appear,</hi> and <hi>live</hi> for <hi>ever,</hi> contrary to <hi>all</hi> the <hi>malice</hi> and <hi>enmity</hi> of the <hi>Devil;</hi> then (rather than he will submit to be no more) he will transform himself, and take upon him the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> of his <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> and profess him in <hi>words,</hi> and seem a <hi>Friend</hi> to <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom:</hi> And this he doth, that he may live still in the <hi>world,</hi> and by <hi>deceiveableness</hi> beguile the sons of men into perpetual destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:199695:24"/>9. And the very work of <hi>Antichrist</hi> this day in the world, is to <hi>deceive, beguile, seduce</hi> and <hi>betray</hi> the <hi>world</hi> and all <hi>mankind;</hi> 'tis his onely <hi>work</hi> and <hi>calling,</hi> as I may say, to <hi>deceive,</hi> 'tis his <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>property</hi> to <hi>work deceitfully;</hi> and thus it ever was with him, it hath been his <hi>property</hi> and his <hi>work</hi> in <hi>all ages,</hi> and in <hi>every age</hi> since the <hi>beginning</hi> of the <hi>world,</hi> to <hi>deceive</hi> and <hi>beguile,</hi> to <hi>lead</hi> men from <hi>God,</hi> and to <hi>lead</hi> them into <hi>perdition;</hi> this I say hath ever been his work in the world, and by the means aforesaid, (to wit) by <hi>transforming</hi> and <hi>changing</hi> himself into the likeness of <hi>righteousness</hi> and <hi>verity,</hi> and putting the <hi>pretence</hi> of <hi>goodness, virtue</hi> and <hi>holiness</hi> upon his <hi>actions</hi> and <hi>doings,</hi> though never so <hi>evil</hi> and <hi>unrighteous,</hi> he hath always, I say, by this <hi>means,</hi> and in this <hi>way deceived</hi> the <hi>world,</hi> by appearing as a <hi>Saint,</hi> as a <hi>well-doer,</hi> as an <hi>angel</hi> of <hi>Light,</hi> pretending <hi>wisdom, righteousness</hi> and <hi>virtue,</hi> and coloring his deeds thereby, as is proved in the <hi>case</hi> of the first <hi>deceiving</hi> of <hi>Eve;</hi> What said <hi>Satan</hi> to the <hi>Woman?</hi> Not that <hi>I am such a one, and do intend to deceive thee with falsity;</hi> but, <hi>Thou shalt be as God; Thou shalt be wise of thy self, and know, and be, and do as God:</hi> Here was a <hi>fair pretence,</hi> by which he <hi>deceived</hi> the <hi>Woman.</hi> And the <hi>false Prophets</hi> and <hi>false Apostles</hi> in the days of old, did not <hi>deceive</hi> the <hi>world</hi> into an <hi>absolute denial</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Christ,</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> but did <hi>deceive</hi> them into the <hi>false Profession</hi> of the same, holding out the <hi>form</hi> of <hi>godliness</hi> without the <hi>power;</hi> and by <hi>feigned words,</hi> and <hi>good speeches,</hi> did <hi>deceive</hi> the <hi>hearts</hi> of the <hi>simple;</hi> and by <hi>false Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> and <hi>Ordinances,</hi> and <hi>Form</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> did the <hi>Antichrist</hi> deceive the <hi>World</hi> in dayes past, as he doth at <hi>this day:</hi> For if he did appear to be as he is in his in his <hi>own nature</hi> and <hi>property,</hi> a <hi>Devil, Deceiver,</hi> and <hi>wicked one,</hi> a <hi>Leader</hi> to <hi>Perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>Destruction,</hi> and should vindicate himself as such, and <hi>entice</hi> and <hi>tempt</hi> people as such; then none would <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi> him, nor <hi>follow</hi> his <hi>wayes,</hi> for none would <hi>willingly</hi> be <hi>destroyed.</hi> But he appears not as such in the <hi>world,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes <hi>transforms</hi> himself into the <hi>likeness</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Goodness,</hi> still pretending the same: And by this <hi>means</hi> is he more <hi>capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> to <hi>deceive mankind;</hi> for he cannot so readily <hi>deceive</hi> and <hi>lead</hi> men to <hi>perdition</hi> in his <hi>own proper Nature,</hi> if he appear
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:199695:25"/> as he is such: But therefore he appears <hi>contrary</hi> to what his own <hi>nature</hi> is, and <hi>transforms</hi> himself. And thus doth <hi>Antichrist</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the <hi>Christian World</hi> (so called) at this day, even by his <hi>false wayes</hi> of <hi>Religion, false Worship, false Doctrine, false Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, false Faith,</hi> and <hi>false Church,</hi> pretending <hi>zeal</hi> and <hi>sanctity,</hi> and such like: Herein and hereby (generally) doth <hi>Antichrist</hi> that <hi>Man of Sin,</hi> deceive and beguile the <hi>World</hi> unto <hi>perdition</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction.</hi> Oh! how many thousands of <hi>Peoples,</hi> of <hi>Nations</hi> and <hi>Countreys,</hi> are at this day <hi>deceived</hi> on this wise, thinking they are in the <hi>truth,</hi> and <hi>true way of Religion, Faith</hi> and <hi>Worship, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing</hi> and <hi>performing</hi> these things with much zeal, as if they were indeed the <hi>wayes</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> when as they are but <hi>false, feigned, formal,</hi> and of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and <hi>deceivable</hi> to the <hi>souls</hi> of <hi>men,</hi> even <hi>shews</hi> without <hi>substance; forms</hi> without <hi>life</hi> and <hi>power;</hi> of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and not of the <hi>true Christ.</hi> And thus, and after this manner, with the very <hi>likeness</hi> of <hi>Righteousness,</hi> and <hi>appearance</hi> of <hi>Godliness,</hi> and <hi>profession</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>duty</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> hath <hi>Antichrist</hi> deceived the <hi>world,</hi> and doth at this day <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude Nations,</hi> to the <hi>perdition</hi> of <hi>thousands:</hi> And <hi>Antichrist</hi> doth not generally deceive men in his <hi>works</hi> and <hi>appearance</hi> as he is in his own proper <hi>Nature;</hi> but in his appearance and works trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed and changed into another <hi>likeness,</hi> even into the <hi>likeness</hi> of <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>righteousness:</hi> By this means and way <hi>Satan, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ,</hi> and that <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>Sin,</hi> doth <hi>delude</hi> and <hi>deceive</hi> the <hi>Nations</hi> of the <hi>world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. What the <hi>Works</hi> of <hi>Antichrist</hi> are, by what is said, doth partly appear: His <hi>Works</hi> are all <hi>deceivableness,</hi> to <hi>deceive</hi> and <hi>delude</hi> the <hi>world,</hi> to lead <hi>mankind</hi> captive in the wayes of <hi>sin</hi> and <hi>death,</hi> unto the <hi>destruction</hi> of their <hi>souls,</hi> and to be <hi>cruel</hi> and <hi>hard-hearted, envious, malicious</hi> and <hi>perverse,</hi> a <hi>hater</hi> and <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutor</hi> of <hi>goodnesse</hi> and <hi>good men,</hi> and to <hi>murder</hi> and <hi>work wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness,</hi> to do <hi>all evil,</hi> and to oppose, gain-say and deny <hi>all good:</hi> This in <hi>general</hi> is the <hi>work</hi> of <hi>Antichrist;</hi> though as to particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars I now intend not to mention, saving as I have before shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to impose upon <hi>Conscience</hi> in <hi>Religious matters,</hi> by <hi>outward force</hi> and <hi>violence,</hi> is a main principal work of <hi>Antichrist;</hi> and to <hi>kill</hi> and <hi>destroy</hi> persons on the account of <hi>Heresie</hi> and <hi>Error,</hi> and to use <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:199695:25"/> and <hi>cruel impositions</hi> in <hi>spiritual Cases,</hi> contrary to the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ Jesus.</hi> These are <hi>works</hi> and <hi>ways</hi> of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> which lie brings forth in the <hi>World,</hi> as also the promoting of all the <hi>false</hi> and <hi>Idolatrous Worships,</hi> and <hi>false Church-Governments</hi> in the World; and in short, every <hi>evil work</hi> and <hi>word</hi> brought forth amongst the <hi>sons</hi> of <hi>men,</hi> are the <hi>Works</hi> of the <hi>Devil</hi> and <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ,</hi> which he seduceth the <hi>World</hi> into the working and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of; and to consider the state of the <hi>World</hi> as it is at this day, and how it is deceived into many grievous and abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable wayes of <hi>Error, Superstitions, Idolatries</hi> and <hi>Wickedness,</hi> it makes the hearts of the Righteous sad and mournful, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of the deceivableness of the working of the <hi>Mysterie</hi> of <hi>Iniquity,</hi> of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> that <hi>Man of Sin</hi> in the World, who deceiveth <hi>Mankind</hi> with the appearance and shew of <hi>godliness,</hi> and leads the <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>Men</hi> in the ways of <hi>Ignorance, Death, B lindness</hi> and <hi>Error,</hi> yet holds them under a <hi>false perswasion</hi> of <hi>safety</hi> and <hi>security,</hi> as if they were in the <hi>right way,</hi> and walked in the pathes of <hi>Happiness,</hi> when indeed and in truth they are <hi>beguiled</hi> and <hi>deceived,</hi> and nigh unto the pathes of <hi>Perdition.</hi> Oh! how hath <hi>Antichrist</hi> prevailed in these latter dayes, since the dayes of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> and <hi>deceived</hi> the <hi>world</hi> with the very <hi>formal profession</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> of such <hi>Doctrines</hi> and <hi>Things</hi> as the <hi>Apostles</hi> held and practised in the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in their dayes: But now <hi>Antichrist</hi> he holds the <hi>form</hi> in his <hi>false Spirit,</hi> and hath the appearance and likenesse of <hi>Righteousnesse, Truth, Faith</hi> and <hi>Worship,</hi> without the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> even the likenesse of the things that the <hi>Apostles</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> held in the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>God:</hi> And hereby is the World deceived, though <hi>Antichrist</hi> hath taught them to plead <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and prove by <hi>Scriptures,</hi> that the Apostles did the same things, and held the same Profession; yet being now held and professed our of the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and not in the same <hi>Spirit</hi> that the Apostles were in, 'tis but of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and deceiveable, and leads <hi>captive</hi> the <hi>souls</hi> of <hi>men</hi> into <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction.</hi> Oh therefore that the <hi>World,</hi> and all that dwel there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, would consider the danger of that <hi>deceivable Spirit</hi> of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ,</hi> and how he <hi>deceiveth mankind,</hi> and would turn from
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:199695:26"/> him, and forsake the <hi>wayes</hi> and <hi>works</hi> of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> that they may be <hi>saved,</hi> and not <hi>destroyed.</hi> Oh! all ye called <hi>Christians,</hi> 'tis time to consider what <hi>spirit</hi> ye are of, and what <hi>spirit</hi> leads you, and how ye may escape his <hi>delusions;</hi> for the <hi>Day</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> is come, and he is gathering <hi>People</hi> out of the <hi>wayes</hi> of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist,</hi> and setting them <hi>free</hi> from his <hi>cruel Bonds,</hi> to serve the <hi>Lord</hi> in <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Freedom</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ Jesus;</hi> and blessed are all they that <hi>witness</hi> this, where <hi>Christ</hi> reigns, and <hi>Antichrist</hi> is subdued with his <hi>works</hi> and <hi>fruits,</hi> and discovered and destroyed by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and the <hi>brightness</hi> of his <hi>Coming,</hi> who comes to judge the <hi>World</hi> in <hi>Righteousnesse</hi> and <hi>Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. These things are said in general of <hi>Antichrist;</hi> Now it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains to be shewed, <hi>What the Government of</hi> Antichrist <hi>is in it self,</hi> and <hi>where it is in being,</hi> and <hi>who the Subjects of his Kingdom are.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Antichrist</hi> the <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>Sin</hi> hath a <hi>Government,</hi> a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> a <hi>Power,</hi> an <hi>Authority,</hi> a <hi>Rule</hi> and a <hi>Dominion</hi> (which is indeed his <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi>) this is not <hi>doubtful</hi> to <hi>any,</hi> but <hi>acknowledged</hi> by <hi>all;</hi> but what this <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> is, many are ignorant. Now the <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>Antichrist</hi> is not the <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> of some <hi>particular man,</hi> in some <hi>particular Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey</hi> and <hi>Nation</hi> upon Earth, distinct from all other <hi>Persons</hi> and <hi>Nations,</hi> as if such a particular <hi>visible Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> were <hi>Antichrist's Government,</hi> and none besides: But the <hi>Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>Antichrist</hi> is more <hi>invisible,</hi> more <hi>hidden,</hi> as it were more <hi>spiritual</hi> and <hi>undiscernable</hi> unto the sons of men, than any <hi>visible, outward Kingdom</hi> is: And indeed, the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Antichrist</hi> is the <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Spiritual Wickedness,</hi> of <hi>spiritual, invisible Iniquity,</hi> or the <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion</hi> of the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>Perdition,</hi> of the <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>Sin,</hi> exercised in the hearts and spirits of all <hi>ungodly men:</hi> This is the <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> an <hi>authority</hi> of <hi>spiritual wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,</hi> a <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>Mysterie</hi> of <hi>Iniquity,</hi> and of <hi>invisible pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing</hi> of the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>Perdition</hi> in, and over the hearts of the <hi>sons</hi> of <hi>men;</hi> not onely of <hi>one person,</hi> or in <hi>one Nation</hi> or <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of the <hi>world,</hi> but in <hi>all sinful persons,</hi> and over <hi>all Nations</hi> of the Earth; <hi>Antichrist's Government</hi> is such throughout <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:199695:26"/> of this world, even a <hi>Spiritual Power</hi> of <hi>Wickedness,</hi> a <hi>domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> and <hi>authority</hi> of the <hi>Mysterie</hi> of <hi>Iniquity,</hi> ruling and reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the <hi>hearts</hi> of many men, even of <hi>all sinful men,</hi> of <hi>all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>just men,</hi> of <hi>all unconverted men</hi> through <hi>all Nations</hi> in the World: So that it may not be truly said, that <hi>Antichrist's Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> is onely the <hi>particular authority</hi> of any <hi>particular man,</hi> in a <hi>particular Nation</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> and all others (<hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Nations</hi>) are free; but it is (as I have said) the <hi>Authority, Power</hi> and <hi>Rule</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Wickedness,</hi> of the <hi>Mysterie</hi> of <hi>Iniquity,</hi> in the hearts of <hi>all evil men,</hi> in <hi>all Nations</hi> through the World. And this is tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Antichrist</hi> in it self.</p>
            <p n="12">12. This <hi>Government</hi> is placed and set up, and chiefly the place and being of it, is (not onely in <hi>all Nations</hi> at large, but) in the <hi>hearts,</hi> even in particular <hi>hearts</hi> of the sons of men, in the <hi>heart</hi> and <hi>inward parts</hi> of man, is the place where <hi>Antichrist's Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> is; his <hi>authority, power</hi> and <hi>dominion,</hi> is in the <hi>hearts</hi> of the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly,</hi> in the <hi>inward parts</hi> of <hi>transgressors;</hi> in the heart <hi>Antichrist</hi> (that <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>Sin</hi>) dwells and works, according as it is written, 2 <hi>Thess.</hi> 2.9, 10 speaking of that man of sin whose <hi>coming is after the working of Satan with all lying wonders, and with all deceivableness of unrighteousness in them that perish;</hi> His dwelling and working is <hi>in them that perish,</hi> in the <hi>ungodly,</hi> in the <hi>hypocrites,</hi> in all <hi>idolaters,</hi> in all <hi>false Worshippers:</hi> Thus it is manifest, that the <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>Antichrist</hi> is <hi>in the heart,</hi> not onely of <hi>one man</hi> in <hi>some Nations,</hi> but <hi>in the hearts</hi> of <hi>all</hi> such men men mentioned, in <hi>all</hi> the Kingdoms of the World, even the <hi>mysterie</hi> of <hi>iniquity,</hi> the <hi>spiritual wickedness,</hi> the <hi>authority</hi> and <hi>power</hi> of that Spirit that is against <hi>Christ,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to him (which is the <hi>Rule, Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ</hi>) dwells and works in the hearts of the sons of men, even like as <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> dwells and walks <hi>in his Saints,</hi> as it is written, so accordingly doth <hi>Antichrist</hi> dwell and walk in all that are the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects</hi> of his <hi>Kingdom:</hi> Yet notwithstanding, the <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist</hi> is <hi>in the hearts</hi> of men, originally there, as having got <hi>domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> and <hi>power</hi> over the <hi>seed</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and placed it self <hi>in the heart,</hi> which is its seat, and where <hi>Christ</hi> should reign; yet the <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>Antichrist</hi> is not so <hi>spiritual,</hi> so <hi>hidden</hi> and <hi>invisible in the heart,</hi> but that it appears <hi>outwardly</hi> and <hi>visibly</hi> in the <hi>actions</hi> and <hi>fruits</hi> of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:199695:27"/> men; so that the <hi>outward actions</hi> and <hi>works</hi> of men are <hi>leavened</hi> and <hi>siasted</hi> with the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and his <hi>Government</hi> appears <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tble</hi> in <hi>Antichristian wayes</hi> and <hi>works</hi> brought forth by men; the <hi>sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness</hi> of men, the <hi>hypocrisies</hi> of men, the <hi>idolatries</hi> of men, and the <hi>false principles</hi> and <hi>doctrines</hi> of men, which appear visibly, are the <hi>works</hi> of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and his <hi>Government</hi> stands in these things; in these <hi>works</hi> he governs men, and to the doing of them he leads and rules men by his Authority and Power, which is <hi>in</hi> the hearts of men. And thus <hi>Antichrist's Government</hi> appears visible and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and is in the <hi>outward actions</hi> and <hi>works</hi> of men to be seen in the world, as well as the working of his <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> is in the <hi>heart, inwardly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And also <hi>Antichrist's Government</hi> is extended not onely, as first, dwelling and working in the <hi>hearts</hi> of the <hi>ungodly;</hi> nor secondly, as over the <hi>works</hi> of men particularly; but over the <hi>Governments</hi> of <hi>many Nations</hi> and <hi>Countreys</hi> in general, is <hi>Antichrists Power</hi> and <hi>Rule</hi> extended; so that the <hi>Governments</hi> of the world are <hi>levened</hi> and <hi>tasted</hi> with <hi>Antichristian Power</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> in many <hi>Nations,</hi> even the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Antichrist</hi> hath possessed many <hi>hearts,</hi> many <hi>works,</hi> and not onely so, but many <hi>Governments</hi> amongst men; and this hath appeared and broken forth visible in all the <hi>works</hi> of <hi>unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness, injustice, oppressions</hi> and <hi>persecutions,</hi> brought forth in <hi>worldly Governments;</hi> for so much as hath been brought forth in any <hi>Government,</hi> in any <hi>Nation,</hi> at any time, of <hi>unrighteousnesse, injustice, oppression, idolatry, false worship</hi> and <hi>persecutions,</hi> and of any other evils, even so much of <hi>Antichrist's Kingdom, Government</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> hath been in that <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Government;</hi> and that <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> wheresoever, in what <hi>Nation</hi> and <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey</hi> soever, hath been <hi>Antichristian,</hi> even in so much, and by so much as <hi>Injustice, Wickedness, Cruelty, Persecution,</hi> or any acts of <hi>sin</hi> and <hi>wickedness</hi> have been, or are brought forth into action in that <hi>Government.</hi> And thus it is manifest what, and where <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ</hi>'s <hi>Government</hi> is: Now I shall briefly shew who the <hi>subjects</hi> of his <hi>Kingdom</hi> are.</p>
            <p n="1">1. All the <hi>ungodly, unrighteous,</hi> and <hi>unconverted</hi> persons in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral throughout the world, are the <hi>Subjects</hi> of <hi>Antichrists Kingdom,</hi> all the sons of fallen <hi>Adam,</hi> in transgression, all that are in the <hi>first
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:199695:27"/> birth,</hi> in <hi>degeneration,</hi> in the <hi>alienation</hi> and <hi>separation</hi> from <hi>God;</hi> even all that are <hi>wicked,</hi> and do <hi>wickedly,</hi> that are in the <hi>Enmity</hi> against <hi>Christ,</hi> and <hi>unholy, unsanctified,</hi> and <hi>unregenerate,</hi> these are all of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrists Kingdom, subjects</hi> of it, and <hi>servants</hi> to it, and it rules <hi>in</hi> them, and <hi>over</hi> them, and <hi>Antichrist</hi> is their <hi>Ruler</hi> in all these their <hi>wicked wayes,</hi> and in this their present state and condition.</p>
            <p n="2">2. All <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> that profess God in <hi>words,</hi> and in <hi>works</hi> deny him, that make a shew of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Worship,</hi> when their <hi>hearts</hi> are far from the <hi>Lord;</hi> that with their mouths profess much <hi>love</hi> to God, and with their lips <hi>honor</hi> him, but are departed from his <hi>fear,</hi> and stand not in his <hi>Counsel,</hi> all such are <hi>subjects</hi> of the <hi>goverment</hi> of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> even all <hi>false-hearted, dissembling Hypocrites,</hi> that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess more of God, then they know of him by the <hi>operation</hi> of his <hi>Spirit;</hi> that have an <hi>outward conformity</hi> in appearance, of <hi>worship,</hi> and <hi>duty</hi> to <hi>God-wards,</hi> and their <hi>hearts</hi> are not conformed to the <hi>Power</hi> of God, by his <hi>Spirit;</hi> all such are of the Government of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and his <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> dwells in them, and they are under the Dominion thereof.</p>
            <p n="3">3. All <hi>Idolaters, false-worshippers, Hereticks</hi> and <hi>erroneous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons;</hi> such as <hi>cry up Church</hi> and <hi>Ministry,</hi> and <hi>profess Faith</hi> and <hi>Godliness,</hi> and yet are not <hi>guided</hi> by the <hi>Spirit of Christ,</hi> nor <hi>led</hi> of <hi>it</hi> into all <hi>Truth,</hi> these are <hi>subjects</hi> of the aforesaid <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of <hi>Antichrist;</hi> even all they that are <hi>sensually minded,</hi> and have not the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> guiding them in the <hi>way</hi> of <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness</hi> and <hi>truth,</hi> who are not <hi>converted</hi> and <hi>born again,</hi> and <hi>renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> into the <hi>image</hi> and <hi>likeness</hi> of <hi>Christ Jesus;</hi> and yet practices <hi>holiness,</hi> and <hi>duty</hi> to <hi>Godwards</hi> in <hi>outward appearance,</hi> and are in the <hi>profession</hi> of the <hi>words</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apostles,</hi> but have not the <hi>same spirit</hi> and <hi>power</hi> of the <hi>Lord Jesus Christ</hi> as the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apostles</hi> had, these are covered with <hi>sheeps-cloathing,</hi> and <hi>professes Christ,</hi> and <hi>his words,</hi> but are against <hi>Christ,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to <hi>Him</hi> in <hi>kind</hi> and <hi>nature;</hi> and all such are of the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and hee <hi>governs</hi> them, and <hi>rules</hi> over them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. All <hi>Back-sliders,</hi> and them that have forsaken the <hi>right way</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> all that are <hi>turned</hi> against the <hi>Truth</hi> of <hi>God</hi> which once they <hi>knew</hi> and <hi>believed,</hi> and were <hi>convinced</hi> of, and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:199695:28"/>
               <hi>professed,</hi> these are all <hi>subjects</hi> of <hi>Antichrist's raign</hi> and <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> even all the <hi>unfaithful</hi> and <hi>false-hearted,</hi> who are <hi>treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous</hi> to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>men,</hi> and <hi>unconstant</hi> and <hi>changeable, time-servers</hi> and <hi>hypocrits,</hi> who have denied <hi>Christ</hi> before <hi>men,</hi> and turned against him, and against his Saints, such are under <hi>Satans</hi> power, and he works in their hearts, and <hi>Antichrist</hi> deceivs them, and they are under his <hi>power</hi> and <hi>dominion,</hi> and are <hi>subjects</hi> of his <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. All <hi>persecutors</hi> of the <hi>Saints,</hi> all <hi>violent</hi> and <hi>cruel</hi> men, all that <hi>persecutes</hi> such as are <hi>contrary-minded</hi> to themselves, are of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and <hi>subjects</hi> of his <hi>kingdom;</hi> even all that <hi>kill,</hi> and <hi>burn,</hi> and <hi>destroy</hi> for difference of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> who them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves profess love to God, and his <hi>Way,</hi> and yet will <hi>persecute</hi> others, and <hi>destroy</hi> them by <hi>cruel dealing;</hi> and that would not suffer any to live but themselves, and will not <hi>do to others as they would be done unto,</hi> but hates the <hi>Neighbour,</hi> and persecutes <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and <hi>imposes</hi> upon his <hi>Conscience</hi> in things against <hi>good Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> and are violent doers; all such men are <hi>Subjects</hi> of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ's Kingdom,</hi> in <hi>all Nations</hi> throughout the world. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let all consider, this is the <hi>Day</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> God will disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and destroy <hi>Antichrist</hi> and his <hi>Kingdom:</hi> Let the <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>ungodly</hi> turn from his <hi>evil way,</hi> lest God destroy him with perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual destruction.</p>
            <p>Lastly, 'tis the property of such who are <hi>subjects</hi> of <hi>Antichrists Kingdom,</hi> to <hi>profess</hi> and <hi>cry up</hi> much of <hi>Christ</hi> in <hi>words,</hi> of what he <hi>said</hi> and <hi>did,</hi> of his <hi>life,</hi> of his <hi>death,</hi> of what he <hi>hath been,</hi> and what he <hi>shall be,</hi> and yet to deny the <hi>present enjoyment</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> to that <hi>Antichrist</hi> is an enemy; he can well away with it to <hi>speak</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> at a <hi>distance,</hi> but he cannot bear it if any hold forth a <hi>present enjoyment</hi> of <hi>Christ;</hi> that <hi>Christ</hi> takes away <hi>sin,</hi> and <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gives it,</hi> and that his <hi>blood</hi> cleanseth from it, and that he is the <hi>Justifier,</hi> and the <hi>Redeemer</hi> and <hi>Saviour;</hi> the <hi>profession</hi> of all this in <hi>words</hi> from the <hi>letter</hi> without, and that they are things true in themselves, <hi>Antichrist</hi> can bear and make a shew of in <hi>profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,</hi> but if any of the <hi>Saints</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> do <hi>witness</hi> these things, and shall testifie in the <hi>power</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> the <hi>enjoyment</hi> of these things, and that they are at present in this life possessed (to wit) <hi>Christ</hi> now <hi>lives</hi> in us, and is <hi>come,</hi> and his <hi>blood</hi> hath <hi>cleansed</hi> from <hi>sin,</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:199695:28"/> and he hath <hi>forgiven</hi> it, and he hath <hi>justified, redeemed</hi> and <hi>saved;</hi> I say if any do <hi>witness</hi> these things in <hi>present enjoyment,</hi> and that they are now in this present time <hi>witnessed</hi> in the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and not onely <hi>professed</hi> from the <hi>Letter</hi> without, but <hi>experienced</hi> by the <hi>work</hi> of <hi>God</hi> within; <hi>Antichrist</hi> opposeth this, and gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saies <hi>present enjoyment,</hi> and such indeed are <hi>subjects</hi> of <hi>Antichrists Kingdom,</hi> who have the <hi>profession</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> in <hi>words,</hi> but no <hi>present enjoyment</hi> of him, but wants <hi>his nature,</hi> and are in the <hi>nature con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary</hi> to him, and feeds upon reports of things done by him without, and upon the expectations of what he shall do here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, and in their <hi>present state</hi> are <hi>without Christ,</hi> and are <hi>sinners</hi> and <hi>transgressors</hi> against the <hi>life of righteousness, unconverted</hi> and <hi>unregenerated</hi> by <hi>Christ,</hi> all such as these are the <hi>subjects</hi> of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ</hi> his <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as concerning the <hi>Rise</hi> and <hi>Fall</hi> of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> the <hi>begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> and <hi>ending</hi> of his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> these things in season may be declared, if God permit.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 2. line 27. for <hi>were</hi> read <hi>way:</hi> and line 28. between <hi>exercised upon them</hi> and <hi>converted,</hi> read <hi>they were.</hi> p. 27. l. 32. for <hi>end</hi> read <hi>and.</hi> p. 34. l. 18. for <hi>loving</hi> read <hi>lying;</hi> and what else is amiss, rather correct then blame.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>